<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="lm-admin" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Leave Management Administrative Tools</title>
	<section>
		<title>Accrual Category</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/accrualcatmaintcompact.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>Accrual Category Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>Accrual Category Fields :</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the override will go into effect.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Short code used to identify the accrual category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text description for the accrual category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
						<entry>Leave Plan under which the accrual category will reside.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Earn Interval</entry>
						<entry>An interval of time that should pass, if any, between accruals.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Proration</entry>
						<entry>On/Off flag used to pro-rate accruals for partial earn intervals.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Unit of Time</entry>
						<entry>The units associated with accruals. Either days or hours.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Min Percent Worked to Earn Accrual</entry>
						<entry>Defines a minimum percentage of an accrual interval needed in terms of time worked, in order to receive some accrual under this category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Donation</entry>
						<entry>Flag indicating whether this accrual cateogry is eligible for donations.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Show on Grid</entry>
						<entry>Yes/No Flag indicating whether the accrual category is to appear on time sheets and/or Leave Calendars within summaries.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Default Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>The underlying earn code used to report leave under this accrual category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Category Has Rules</entry>
						<entry>Yes/No flag indicating whether the accrual category has associated rules.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Flag indicating activity. If checked, 'Y', indicates the record will become active as of the effective date. If unchecked, 'N',
							indicates the record is to become inactive as of the effective date.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<section>
			<title>Accrual Category Rule</title>
	        <mediaobject>
	            <imageobject>
	                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/accrualrulecompact.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
	            </imageobject>
	            <caption>Accrual Category Rule Maintenance</caption>
	        </mediaobject>
	        <para>Accrual Category Rule's are maintained within Accrual Cateogry Maintenance. In order to define a rule, the owning Accrual Category must indicate
	        	'Yes' for Category Has Rules.</para>
        <table frame="none">
            <title>Accrual Category Fields :</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Service Unit of Time</entry>
                        <entry>Unit of time associated with the start and end fields.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Start</entry>
                        <entry>When added to an employee's service date, defines the start of the service interval under which this rule will be in effect.
                        	There should be no gaps nor overlap when defining more than one rule. 0 (Zero) is a valid entry for Start.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>End</entry>
                        <entry>When added to an employee's service date, defines the end of the service interval under which this rule will no longer be in effect.
                        	There should be no gaps nor overlap when defining more than one rule.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Accrual Rate</entry>
                        <entry>The amount of leave that will accrue over a full Accrual Earn Interval, defined on the Accrual Category. This value uses the units
                        	supplied in the Accrual Category's Unit of Time field. NOTE: This is NOT the Accrual Category Rule's 'Service Unit of Time' field.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Max Bal Flag</entry>
                        <entry>Yes/No flag used to indicate that a maximum balance limit will be in effect during this rules service interval.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                    	<entry>Max Balance</entry>
                    	<entry>The maximum balance allowed for the accrual category while the employee resides within this rule's service interval.
                    		This is a required field if Max Bal Flag is set to 'Yes'.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Max Balance Action Frequency</entry>
                        <entry>Defines a frequency with which an Action at Max Balance may occur; Leave Approve - once at the end of every leave period,
                        	Year End - once at the end of the leave plan's calendar year. On-Demand - at the employee's discretion.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Action at Max Balance</entry>
                        <entry>Provides three options; Transfer, Payout or Lose (forfeit). This action should occur with the given frequency only if an employee has
                        	exceeded the Max Balance as of the end of the frequency period.</entry>
                    </row>
					<row>
						<entry>Max Balance Transfer to Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>If 'Transfer' is selected action, the transaction will place the converted leave amount into the supplied Max Balance Transfer to Accrual Category,
							and will be made available for use via the Max Balance Transfer to Accrual Category's default earn code.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Max Balance Transfer Conversion Factor</entry>
						<entry>A conversion factor used to adjust the actual amount credited to the Max Balance Transfer to Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Max Transfer Amount</entry>
						<entry>Optionally defines a maximum amount that the employee is allowed to transfer when conducting a transfer.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Max Payout Amount</entry>
						<entry>Optionally defines a maximum amount that the employee is allowed to pay out when conducting a payout</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Max Payout Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>if 'Payout' is selected action, the transaction will place the un-converted leave amount into the supplied Max Payout Earn Code.
							This code will likely be in tight relationship to payroll.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Max Usage</entry>
						<entry>The given amount, in the accrual category's Unit of Time, places a ceiling on the amount of leave an employee is allowed to used over
							the leave plan's calendar year.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Max Carryover</entry>
						<entry>The given amount, in the accrual category's Unit of Time, places a ceiling on the amount of leave an employee is allowed to carryover into
							a subsequent leave plan calendar year.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Flag indicating activity. When checked, 'Y', the rule will be effective as of the Accrual Category's effective date. Any employee
							who's service amount falls within the start and end dates [end date exclusive] shall be included under this rule. When unchecked, 'N', the
							record shall become inactive as of the Accrual Category's effective date.</entry>
					</row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>
        	For a detailed examination of Accrual Category Rules including configuration examples, please consult the
        	<link xlink:href="https://wiki.kuali.org/display/KPMEDOC/KPME+System+Administration+Guide">Leave Management Configuration</link> guide.
        </para>
		</section>
	</section>
    <section>
        <title>Balance Transfer</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/balancetransfermaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Balance Transfer Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Balance Transfer Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>
            Department, Location, and System Administrators have access to create and view Balance Transfer maintenance documents.  Admins can access this 
            document to perform transactions that are not triggered by the Accrual Category’s Max Balance limit.  
            A new balance transfer record will create up to three leave blocks on the employee’s leave calendar as of the record's effective date.
        </para>
        <table frame="none">
            <title>Balance Transfer fields :</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>Date the balance transfer will go into effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier of the employee.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Transfer From Accrual Category</entry>
                        <entry>The Accrual Category to transfer the amount from.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Transfer Amount</entry>
                        <entry>The amount to transfer.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Forfeited Amount</entry>
                        <entry>The computed amount that will be forfeited.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Transfer To Accrual Category</entry>
                        <entry>The Accrual Category to transfer the amount to.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Amount Transferred</entry>
                        <entry>The final amount transferred.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
	<section>
		<title>Employee Override</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/employeeoverridemaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Employee Override Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Employee Override Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
		<para>
			The system will allow for the ability to override the Accrual Category limits, such as usage, carryover, transfer or payout, for an individual 
			employee.  The system will check to see if the employee has an exception every time the logic is executed for
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        Max Balance – The system will use the indicated override value as the Accrual Category’s max balance.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        Max Transfer/Payout Amount – When a balance transfer transaction is preformed the limit for the maximum amount available to transfer or 
                        payout will be the indicated override value.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
                    <para>
                        Max Usage – On the employee’s leave calendar, when adding usage leave blocks the override value will be used to verify that the limit 
                        has not been exceeded.  On the leave calendar summary grid, the override value will appear in the max usage column for the Accrual 
                        Category.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
                    <para>
                        Max Annual Carryover – Annually, the max carryover is processed with approving the final leave calendar for the year.  The override 
                        value will be used when processing the annual carry over leave block.
                    </para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
            <note>
		        <para>
                    No limit is needed for any of the override types.  For example, if the override type of Max Usage and the Override Value is blank, the 
                    system will not apply a usage limit for this employee’s accrual category that typically has a usage limit.  
		        </para>
            </note>
		</para>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>Employee Override fields :</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the override will go into effect.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Principal ID</entry>
						<entry>Identifier of the employee.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
						<entry>Leave Plan associated with the Principal ID and Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to identify the Accrual Category the override will be applied to.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Type of Override</entry>
						<entry>Accrual Category limit that should be used for the Employee.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Override Value</entry>
						<entry>The new limit value to be used for the Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the reason for the override.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Status of the Override.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<note>
			<para>
				Access will be restricted to System Admins.
			</para>
		</note>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Leave Adjustment</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/leaveadjustmentmaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Leave Adjustment Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Leave Adjustment Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
		<para>
			Ability to modify a employee’s earn code accrual balance.  Restricted to System Admins or Department Admins with options to either create new or 
			view existing donation records.  On submit, a leave block will be generated and displayed on their leave calendar.
		</para>
        <para>
            An employee new to the system may have existing leave time from previous service.  To apply those hours to the employee’s new leave plan and accrual 
            categories, Leave Adjustment document for each accrual category can be create to adjust the employee’s balances to reflect the existing hours.    
        </para>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>Leave Adjustment fields :</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the adjustment will go into effect.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Principal ID</entry>
						<entry>Identifier of the employee.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
						<entry>Leave Plan associated with the Principal ID and Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to identify the Accrual Category the adjustment will be.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>Earn Code associated with the Accrual Category and leave adjustment.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Adjustment Amount</entry>
						<entry>The value of the leave adjustment, positive or negative.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the reason for the adjustment.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<note>
			<para>
				An employee will not have ability to modify their own leave balances.
			</para>
		</note>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Leave Donation</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/leavedonationmaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Leave Donation Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Leave Donation Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
		<para>
			Employee's may donate leave to another employee.  The donation transaction is done by the system admin with option to create new or view existing 
			donation records.  On submit leave blocks are generated for both recipient and donor that will display on their leave calendar. Leave donation may 
			or may not be prorated according to the donor and recipient's salary.  Amount Donated and Amount Received must be manually entered and is what will 
			be removed/added from the designated Accrual Categories.
		</para>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>Leave Donation fields :</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the Donation transaction will go into effect.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Donor's Principal ID</entry>
						<entry>Identifier of the employee donating leave.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Donation Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Accrual Category associated with the donated Leave.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Donation Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>A leave block indicating the amount donated will be recorded with this earn code.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Amount Donated</entry>
						<entry>The amount of accrued leave to be donated. Subtracted from the Donated Leave Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Recipient's Principal ID</entry>
						<entry>Identifier of the employee receiving the donated leave.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Recipient's Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Accrual Category the donated Leave will be accrued to.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Recipient's Earn Code </entry>
						<entry>The donation accrual leave block will be recorded with this earn code.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Amount Received</entry>
						<entry>The amount of accrued leave to be received. Added to the Recipient's Leave Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the reason for the Leave Donation.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>		
	</section>
	<section>
        <title>Leave Payout</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/leavepayoutmaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Leave Payout Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Leave Payout Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>
            Payout maintenance document can be used to payout earned accruals. Department, Location, and System Administrators can use this document to preform 
            payout transactions that are not triggered by the Accrual Category’s Max Balance limit and the payout action.  Example uses of this document include 
            payout of earned accrual at time of termination/retirement.  After a Payout document is submitted leave blocks that reflect
            the payout transaction will be created for the appropriate Accrual Category using the effective date of the payout document. The payout earn code will
            need to be fed to payroll for the payout to be processed.
        </para>
        <table frame="none">
            <title>Leave Payout fields :</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier of the employee.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Earn Code</entry>
                        <entry>Earn code that is associated with the Payout Amount and fed to Payroll.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>Date the leave payout will go into effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Payout From Accrual Category</entry>
                        <entry>Accrual Category to pay leave out of.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Payout Amount</entry>
                        <entry>The amount of leave to pay out.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Forfeited Amount</entry>
                        <entry>Computed amount of accrued leave that will be forfeited.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>        
    </section>
	<section>
        <title>System Scheduled Time Off</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/newsstodoc.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>System Scheduled Time Off [SSTO] Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>SSTO Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>
            SSTO enables the designation of specific dates as "Time Off", supporting several configurations including the ability to bank and transfer unused time.
        </para>
        <table frame="none">
            <title>SSTO Fields :</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>Date the scheduled time off record will go into effect</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Earn Code</entry>
                        <entry>The earn code associated with the scheduled time off.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Accrual Category</entry>
                        <entry>Read-only field, populated from the accrual category field of the given earn code.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Leave Plan</entry>
                        <entry>Read-only field, populated from the leave plan field of the given earn code / accrual category.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Accrued Date</entry>
                        <entry>Date the holiday is available to use.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Scheduled Time Off Date</entry>
                        <entry>Date of the scheduled time off that is put on the calendar.</entry>
                    </row>
					<row>
						<entry>Location</entry>
						<entry>The location in which this SSTO is applicable. Accepts wild card (%).</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the scheduled time off.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Amount of Time</entry>
						<entry>The amount of leave time available for this scheduled time off. Precision is based off Earn Code's Fractional Time Allowed field.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Unused Time</entry>
						<entry>Provides options on how the amount of time can be used. No Unused Time Allowed, Transfer and Bank. For more information
							on the configuration and use of these options, consult the appropriate section in the
							<link xlink:href="https://wiki.kuali.org/display/KPMEDOC/KPME+System+Administration+Guide">Leave Management Configuration Guide</link></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Transfer to Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>If Unused Time is Transfer, the converted amount of time will be made available for use by this earn code.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Transfer Conversion Factor</entry>
						<entry>Converts the amount of time available for use after transfer by this amount.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Premium Holiday</entry>
						<entry>Flag indicating whether this SSTO is a premium holiday. If checked, 'Y', gives certain employees a higher rate of pay when working
							the Scheduled Time Off Date.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Flag indicating activitiy. If checked, 'Y', record will be active as of the effective date. if unchecked, 'N', record will become
							inactive as of the effective date.</entry>
					</row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>        
    </section>
	<section>
        <title>Earn Code - Leave Management Attributes </title>
         <para>
            We seperated Time and Leave attributes into different sections on Earn Code Maintenance Document to better organize the fields and make the GUI more user friendly. 
            Please refer to the field definition of Earn Code in Basic Setup guide.
            <mediaobject>
	            <imageobject>
	                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/EarnCodeLeaveSection.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
	            </imageobject>
	            <textobject>
	                <phrase>Earn Code Maintenance Document - Leave Management Attributes section</phrase>
	            </textobject>
	            <caption>Earn Code Maintenance Document - Leave Management Attributes section</caption>
        	</mediaobject>
        	<para>
	        	<mediaobject>
		            <imageobject>
		                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/EarnCodeLeaveExpanded.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
		            </imageobject>
		            <textobject>
		                <phrase>Earn Code Maintenance Document - Leave Management expanded</phrase>
		            </textobject>
		            <caption>Earn Code Maintenance Document - Leave Management expanded</caption>
	        	</mediaobject>
        	</para>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>