<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="lm-config" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
	<title>Leave Management Configuration</title>
	<para>This chapter discusses the configuration of key leave management business objects. The
		order in which the sections are presented are important in that they generally build on each
		other. That is, to configure an accrual category, a leave plan should already be configured.
		While it is possible to configure a leave plan at the time of accrual category
		configuration, such a configuration would lead to documentation hopping if the reader is not
		already well acquainted with leave plan configuration requirements. Thus it is recommended
		to read this chapter in the order presented. </para>
	<para> The reader should also be familiar with the concepts discussed in the chapter "Basic
		Setup" in order to test the configurations presented in this chapter. </para>
	<section>
		<title>Leave Management Configuration</title>
		<para>This chapter discusses all rules and configurations for Leave Management module of
			KHR. All rules and configurations can be accessed through maintenance documents listed
			under the <emphasis role="bold">Leave Management</emphasis> section on the Time &amp;
			Leave Admin tab. </para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/lm21/leavemaintsection.png" format="png" scale="50"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>Time &amp; Leave Admin</phrase>
			</textobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/lm21/leavemaintchannel.png" format="png" scale="75"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>Leave Maintenance Section</phrase>
			</textobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Leave Plan</title>
		<para> The system supports configurable Leave Plans that can be attached to employees
			(Principal HR Attributes) and/or salary groups (Position Management). Leave Plans are
			used configuring one or more accrual categories. Employees eligible for leave will be
			designated an Leave Plan via the Principal HR Attributes. An employee's leave plan will
			be used to determine the start of their leave calendar year (year to date balances and
			carry over rules), the number of months into the future they can plan their leave, and
			earn codes that the employee is eligible to use on their leave calendars and/or
			timesheets. </para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/lm21/leaveplanmaintdoc.png" format="png" scale="50"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>Leave Plan Maintenance Document</phrase>
			</textobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<table>
			<title>Leave Plan Fields</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.50*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>The Effective date for which the Leave Plan will be
							effective.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to identify the Leave Plan.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the Leave Plan.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Planning Months</entry>
						<entry>Number of months the accrual service will calculate into the future
							and allow planning and submission of leave requests</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Calendar Year Start (MM/DD)</entry>
						<entry>Month and Day (MM/DD) of the start of the leave year (i.e. Calendar
							or Fiscal Year). This date will be used to calculate year to date
							accruals, usages, and balances in the leave summary. </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Batch Prior Year Carry Over Start (MM/DD)</entry>
						<entry>Date batch job should run to create a carry over leave block for each
							accrual category balance from the prior year. This should run will all
							leave calendars from the previous year are final. The leave summary that
							includes accrual balances will use this carry over leave block to
							calculate available balances. </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Batch Prior Year Carry Over Start Time (00:00 AM)</entry>
						<entry>Time batch job should run to create a carry over leave block for each
							accrual category balance from the prior year</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Status of the Leave Plan, checked indicates Active, unchecked
							indicates Inactive.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Accrual Category Configuration</title>
		<para>The system supports the creation of accrual categories within leave plans to establish
			groups of benefit time that can be reported and/or accrued against. Accrual Category
			will define the rules used by the system’s accrual service including proration, maximum
			balances, and establish what happens once maximum balances are reached. </para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/lm21/acccatmaintdoc.png" format="png" scale="50"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>Accrual Category Maintenance Document</phrase>
			</textobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<table>
			<title>Accrual Category Fields</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.50*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>The Effective date for which the Leave Plan will be
							effective.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Code used to identify the Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Description of the Accrual Category</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
						<entry>Leave Plan associated with the Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Earn Interval</entry>
						<entry>Timing when accrued leave is earned. Options: Daily, Weekly,
							Semi-Monthly, Monthly, Yearly, Pay Calendar, No Accrual The Accrual
							Service will create an Accrual timeblock on the last date of the accrual
							period. Pay Calendar can be used for Timekeeping employees that earns
							accrual at the end of each pay period. No Accrual can be used for
							Accrual Categories used for System Scheduled Time Off. </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Proration</entry>
						<entry>Indicate if accrual is prorated based on partial period. For example,
							start date is 10th day of the month for Monthly Accrual Earn Interval
							would be prorated from the start date. If Off, then no leave will be
							accrued until the start of the next accrual period Accrual earn
							Interval.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Unit of Time</entry>
						<entry>Define unit of time for accruing leave. Options: Days Hours</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Min Percent Worked to Earn Accrual</entry>
						<entry>The start or end date must be within the minimum days of the Accrual
							earn Interval. If start or end date is after then no accrual is earned.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Donation</entry>
						<entry>Indicates the accrued leave is eligible to be donated. Leave Donation
							maintenance document will only Donated Accrual Categories that are
							flagged as eligible for donation. </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Show on Grid</entry>
						<entry>Accrual Category will be displayed on the leave summary and leave
							ledger.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Default Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>This earn code will be used by the accrual service and assign to
							accrual timeblocks. This earn code needs to be defined prior to creating
							the Accrual Category. </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Category Has Rules</entry>
						<entry>Flag if accrual category has rules. Accrual Categories for
							transferring leave or for handling System Scheduled Time Off. </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Status of the Leave Plan, checked indicates Active, unchecked
							indicates Inactive.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<tip>
			<para>Prior to creating a new Accrual Category, a Leave Plan and an Earn Code (Accrual
				Category's Default Earn Code) needs to exist. </para>
		</tip>
		<section>
			<title>Accrual Category Rule</title>
			<para>This section describes the configurations necessary to implement common rules for
				an accrual category. To follow along with this section, the reader should complete
				the sections for Leave Plan and Accrual Category configuration, or the objects
				should already be defined in the application. </para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm21/accrulesmaintdoc.png" format="png" scale="50"
					/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Accrual Category Rules</phrase>
				</textobject>
			</mediaobject>
			<para>One accrual category rule can be used to define up to four properties for an
				accrual category;</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Accrual rates</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Maximum balance limits</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Maximum carryover limits</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Usage limits</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para/>
			<section>
				<title>Accrual Rate Configuration</title>
				<para>Accrual Category that is flagged to have Accrual Rules are required to enter
					at least one rule. Accrual Rules are used to defined the amount of leave that is
					accrued based on lenght of service. The employee's service date found in their
					Principal HR Attribute record is used by the accrual service to determined which
					rules should be used to calculate their accrued leave for an Accrual Earn
					Interval. </para>
				<table>
					<title>Accrual Category Rule Fields for configuring Accrual Rate</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
						<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.50*"/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Field</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>Service Unit of Time</entry>
								<entry>Unit of time for measuring service start and end amounts for
									the accrual rule</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Start</entry>
								<entry>Accrual rule begins on the indicated service
									milestone.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>End</entry>
								<entry>Accrual rule ends on the indicated service milestone.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Accrual Rate</entry>
								<entry>Amount accrued for each Accrual Earn Interval.</entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Maximum Balance Limit Configuration</title>
				<para>Maximum Balances limits can be set for each Accrual Category rule. Configuring
					maximum balances for accrual category rules includes setting the max balance
					limit, when max balance actions are triggered, and what happens when max balance
					has been reached. </para>
				<para>When max balance is reached a warning will appear on the employee's Leave
					Calendar.</para>
				<table>
					<title>Accrual Category Rule Fields for configuring Max Balances</title>
					<tgroup cols="2">
						<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
						<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.50*"/>
						<thead>
							<row>
								<entry>Field</entry>
								<entry>Description</entry>
							</row>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<row>
								<entry>Max Balance Flag</entry>
								<entry>The Accrual Rule has a Max Balance limit</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Max Balance</entry>
								<entry>The amount of accrued leave that will trigger maximum balance
									action.</entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Max Balance Action Frequency</entry>
								<entry>When a Max Balance transaction may occur. Leave Approve: When
									a Leave Calendar or Time Detail is submitted for approval max
									balance transaction will be triggered. Year End: When the Leave
									Calendar or Time Detail prior begining of the Leave Plan's
									Calendar Start date is submitted for approval max balance
									transaction will be triggered. On Demand: Once maximum balance
									is reached the employee has the option to request the Action at
									Max Balance (Transfer or Payout) </entry>
							</row>
							<row>
								<entry>Action at Max Balance</entry>
								<entry>Determines the type of transaction that will occure when Max
									Balance is reached and triggered by the Max Balance Action
									Frequency. Transfer: Triggers a Balance Transfer document.
									Payout: Triggers a Payout document. Lose: Leave over the max
									balance limit will be forfieted. </entry>
							</row>
						</tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
				<section>
					<title>Action at Max Balance: Transfer</title>
					<para>Employees will be prompted for a Balance Transfer document populated with
						the Accrual Rule's values. This document will be routed for approval to the
						employee's Work Area approver and Department Payroll Processor. Leave blocks
						for the amount of leave transfered and/or forfeited will appear on the Leave
						Calendar. All pending Balance Transfer documents must be approved before
						Leave Calendars can be approved. </para>
					<table>
						<title>Accrual Category Rule Fields for configuring Transfer at Max
							Balances</title>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
							<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.50*"/>
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry>Field</entry>
									<entry>Description</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>Max Balance Transfer to Accrual Category</entry>
									<entry>Accrual Category that will be be used to accrue the
										transfer.</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>Max Balance Transfer Conversion Factor</entry>
									<entry>The leave can be transferred at a converted rate.</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>Max Transfer Amount</entry>
									<entry>Maximum amount of leave that can be transferred to the
										Transfer Accrual Category. Remaining balance over the max
										balance limit will be forfieted. </entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</table>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Action at Max Balance: Payout</title>
					<para>Employees will be prompted for a Leave Payout document populated with the
						Accrual Rule's values. This document will be routed for approval to the
						employee's Work Area approver and Department Payroll Processor. Leave blocks
						for the amount of leave paid out and/or forfeited will appear on the Leave
						Calendar. All pending Leave Payout documents must be approved before Leave
						Calendars can be approved. </para>
					<table>
						<title>Accrual Category Rule Fields for configuring Transfer at Max
							Balances</title>
						<tgroup cols="2">
							<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
							<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.50*"/>
							<thead>
								<row>
									<entry>Field</entry>
									<entry>Description</entry>
								</row>
							</thead>
							<tbody>
								<row>
									<entry>Max Payout Amount</entry>
									<entry>Maximum amount of leave can be paid out.</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry>Max Payout Earn Code</entry>
									<entry>Earn code used for paying out leave. This earn code can
										be used for a feed to payroll system. </entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</table>
				</section>
				<section>
					<title>Action at Max Balance: Lose</title>
					<para>Employees will be prompted with the amount of leave that will be forfeited
						so accrued balance is no longer at the max balance limit. All the forfeited
						amount will appear on the leave calendar. </para>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Maximum Usage Limit Configuration</title>
				<para>To define a usage limit, simply enter a value into the “Max Usage” field,
					relative to the selected Unit of Time for the accrual category.</para>
				<para>With a maximum usage limit defined, an employee will not be allowed to add
					leave blocks to their calendar if the amount in the leave block, when added to
					the YTD usage (Leave Plan's Calendar Start Date) as of the requested leave date,
					exceeds this limit.</para>
				<note>
					<para>Maximum usage can be overriden through the use of KHR Leave Management's
						Employee Override feature. Please see the Leave Management Administration
						documentation's section on Employee Overrides.</para>
				</note>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Maximum Carryover Limit Configuration</title>
				<para>Maximum Annual Carryover Limit can be set for each Accrual Category rule. With
					a maximum carry over limit defined, the balance for an accrual category will
					automatically be adjusted when submitting a calendar containing the last day of
					the calendar year. This day is derived from the leave plan defined on the
					accrual category to which this rule is attached. This adjustment is achieved by
					placing a leave block in an amount of the adjustment on the employee’s calendar. </para>
				<note>
					<para>Each leave plan has an automated batch carryover process job. Please see
						the Batch Jobs documentation for information on how to automate the
						carryover process.</para>
				</note>
				<note>
					<para>Maximum Carryover can be overriden through the use of KHR's Employee
						Overrides. See the Leave Management Administrative Documentation for Max
						Annual Carry Override configuration.</para>
				</note>
				<section>
					<title>Conjunctive Rules</title>
					<para>When combined with a maximum balance rule, a maximum carry over limit may
						vary its behavior based on the frequency of the balance transaction:</para>
					<section>
						<title>Leave-Approve Max Balance with Max Annual Carryover</title>
						<para>When defined with a Leave-Approve Action, the adjustment amounts for
							both carryover and leave-approve actions are calculated relative to the
							same ending balance; the balance as of the last day of the leave plan’s
							calendar year. Up to four adjustment leave blocks are created with
							status requested, a maximum of three coming from the balance transaction
							and the fourth coming from the carryover adjustment.</para>
						<para>If the max balance action is approved, the requested leave block
							containing the adjustment amount for carryover is re-calculated to
							reflect the resulting balance. If the max balance action is disapproved,
							the requested adjustment amount for carryover needs no
							correction.</para>
					</section>
					<section>
						<title>Year-End Max Balance with Max Annual Carryover</title>
						<para>When defined with a Year-End Action, any amount in excess of the
							carryover limit and up to the maximum balance limit will be included in
							the year-end balance transaction. </para>
					</section>
				</section>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Multiple Accrual Category Rules</title>
				<para>KHR Leave Managment allows accrual categories to be configured with multiple
					rules, each rule covering a non-overlapping service interval.</para>
				<para>To define multiple rules on a single accrual category, each rule must have
					START and END values that do not overlap any other defined rule. There must also
					be no gaps between the end of one rule and the start of another.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
	<!-- 
	<section>
		<title>Max Balance Transactions</title>
		<para>KPME Leave Management makes available three pre-defined transactions and three
			frequencies with which transactions can occur. With the exception of the On-Demand
			frequency, these transactions are triggered automatically, with respect to the frequency
			set within the accrual category’s rules. When the balance of an accrual category has
			been found to be in excess of the maximum limit defined within its rules, a warning will
			appear on exempt employees’ leave calendars, non-exempt leave eligible employees’ time
			calendars, and will also appear on the employee’s approval row within the time and leave
			approval tabs. </para>
		<section>
			<title>Transaction Frequencies</title>
			<para>KPME Leave Management uses the values defined on accrual category rules to
				automatically determine when specific transactions should occur.</para>
			<section>
				<title>On-Demand</title>
				<para>Transactions that occur with this frequency will automatically present a
					button that the user may click to initiate the transaction. This button is made
					available and active when either:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>the employee’s service as of the current date brings them under a rule
							with an On-Demand frequency and the existing balance when this rule
							takes effect is over the limit defined by the rule, or</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>An accrual has occurred in an amount that exceeds the balance limit
							under the given rule.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/ondemandtransferbutton.jpg" format="JPG"
							scale="45"/>
					</imageobject>
					<textobject>
						<phrase>On-Demand Max Balance Action Button Location</phrase>
					</textobject>
					<caption>A max balance transaction rule with frequency On-Demand triggers a
						button when the action can be taken.</caption>
				</mediaobject>
				<para>The button remains available until the employee executes the transaction, a
					rule change occurs under the accrual category or the balance for the accrual
					category is brought below the maximum defined limit via usage, adjustments,
					donation or other means. If no such action occurs before the end of the period
					or a rule change, the button becomes disabled.</para>
				<para>To execute an on-demand balance transaction, employee's must:</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Click the enabled button to be presented with a max balance action
							form. The form will look similar to this:</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/ondemandtransferprompt.jpg"
									format="JPG" scale="40"/>
							</imageobject>
							<textobject>
								<phrase>On-Demand Max Balance Action Dialog</phrase>
							</textobject>
							<caption>The pre-filled values represent the minimum amount needed to
								bring the balance back to its limit, with a maximized transaction
								amount which minimizes loss. If there is forfeiture, the transfer
								amount cannot be increased.</caption>
						</mediaobject>
						<para/>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Review the values in the form, and adjust the transaction amount if
							desired. If the transaction amount is changed, the other values will be
							updated after the form is submitted. If there is an error in the
							transaction amount field, they will be prompted to fix it. </para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/ondemandtransferprompterror.jpg"
									format="JPG" scale="40"/>
							</imageobject>
							<textobject>
								<phrase>On-Demand Max Balance Action Form Error</phrase>
							</textobject>
							<caption>A negative amount was entered into the transfer amount field,
								preventing the form from being submitted.</caption>
						</mediaobject>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/ondemandtransfererrorcorrected.jpg"
									format="JPG" scale="40"/>
							</imageobject>
							<textobject>
								<phrase>Corrected On-Demand Transfer Prompt Error</phrase>
							</textobject>
							<caption>The negative sign has been removed. <note>Notice the values in
									the forfeited amount and amount transferred
								fields.</note></caption>
						</mediaobject>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/ondemandtransferblocks.jpg" format="JPG"
							scale="80"/>
					</imageobject>
					<textobject>
						<phrase>Resulting leave blocks created by this transaction</phrase>
					</textobject>
					<caption>The resulting leave blocks created from the transaction. The forfeited
						amount and amount transferred fields have been updated relative to the
						transfer amount entered.</caption>
				</mediaobject>
				<para>Also note the resulting warning message on the employee's leave
					calendar.</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/ondemandtransferpendingdoc.jpg"
							format="JPG" scale="47"/>
					</imageobject>
					<textobject>
						<phrase>Pending transfer document warning</phrase>
					</textobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Year-End</title>
				<para>Year-end frequency transactions are identical to leave-approve transactions,
					however, are triggered only if</para>
				<orderedlist numeration="lowerroman">
					<listitem>
						<para>The accrued balance is found to be in excess of the max balance limit
							as defined by the rule in effect as of the last day of the final leave
							period in the leave plan’s calendar year.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>This day is within the calendar being submitted for approval.</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				<para>In such a case, employees will be prompted to submit the transaction in a
					similar fashion to leave-approve transactions.</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Leave Approve</title>
				<para>Transactions with this frequency occur when an employee submits a calendar. If
					the accrued balance as of the last day of a leave period is found to be in
					excess of its maximum limits and this day is within the calendar being
					submitted, the employee will be prompted to submit the transaction prior to the
					calendar being routed for approval.</para>
				<note>For non-exempt leave eligible employees if the calendar does not include the
					last day of the leave period, a warning will continue to display, but no
					transaction will be triggered upon submission.</note>
			</section>

		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Transaction Types</title>
			<para>Three transactions are available by default in KPME Leave Management. Transfer,
				Payout and Lose. Each transaction type has differences, some subtle, in their look
				and feel and in their execution. Transfer and Payout are very similar to each other
				in most regard, whereas the Lose action is noticeably different. Here we examine
				each transaction type, including submission walkthroughs and comparisons.</para>
			<section>
				<title>Lose</title>
				<para>This transaction forfeits unused leave and may occur with leave-approve or
					year-end frequencies.</para>
				<para>If the balance of an accrual category is over its limit as of the last day of
					the leave period, when the employee clicks the “Submit for Approval” button,
					they will be presented with a simple dialog to confirm forfeiture of leave in
					excess of this limit.</para>
				<para>To confirm the loss, click “Forfeit”. Otherwise, click cancel to return to the
					calendar. Once the loss is confirmed, a single approved usage leave block will
					be created on the calendar in an amount equal to the forfeited amount, and the
					calendar will immediately resume submission for approval.</para>
				<para>Lose actions do no require approval by department admins.</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Transfer</title>
				<para>This transaction moves leave from one accrual category to another at a
					pre-determined rate. Transfer may occur with any of the three provided
					frequencies. As with the Lose transaction, a Transfer action is triggered upon
					calendar submission when the balance for an accrual category is found to be in
					excess as of the last day of the leave period.</para>
				<para> Instead of a dialog, the Employee is redirected to a page containing solely
					the transfer form. This form is identical to the form presented with On-Demand
					frequencies, but is not contained within a dialog box. Once this form is
					submitted and correctly validated, up to three leave blocks are created on the
					calendar belonging to the document id listed on the form. Each block is created
					with a “requested” status, one for the transfer amount, amount transferred
					(adjusted for any conversion factor) and, if there exists, forfeiture. The
					calendar then resumes normal submission, and the Employee is redirected back to
					the submitted calendar. All Transfer actions require approval by department
					admins </para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Payout</title>
				<para>This transaction moves leave from an accrual category into an earn code that
					can be used by payroll to add to salary or wages. Payout may occur with any of
					the three provided frequencies. As with Transfer and Lose actions, a Payout
					action can be triggered upon submission of a calendar, and follows the same
					basic flow. All Payout actions require approval by department admins.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<para> </para>
		<section>
			<title>Balance Transaction Approval</title>
			<para>With the exception of the Lose action, all balance transactions must go through
				the approval process. When a max balance action is taken by an employee, KPME
				automatically routes the document to the employee's approver. At that time, the
				document will become available in the approvers action list, as well as in document
				search. </para>
			<para>Balance Transfer and Leave Payout Documents (Max Balance Transaction Maintenance
				Documents) must be approved or disapproved before the calendar on which they reside
				can be approved.</para>
			<para>To take system administrative action on a transaction document:</para>
			<note>Department admins can locate pending balance transaction documents in their action
				list.</note>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Open the Document lookup view by clicking <inlinemediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="../images/docsearchbutton.jpg" format="JPG"
									scale="50"/>
							</imageobject>
							<textobject>
								<phrase>Doc Search button</phrase>
							</textobject>
						</inlinemediaobject>, located: </para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/docsearch.jpg" format="JPG" scale="50"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Perform a search, filtering results by one of the provided fields if
						necessary.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Locate the document, and click on the link provided by the document
						id</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/balancedoclookup.jpg" format="JPG"
								scale="47"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>Locating the max balance document</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Enter an annotative remark in the field provided, then select the action
						to take.</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/balancedocaction.jpg" format="JPG"
								scale="47"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>Taking adminstrative action on a Max Balance Transaction
								Maintenance Document</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para/>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/balanceactionapproved.jpg" format="JPG"
						scale="47"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>A Max Balance Action Document after approval</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>This document was approved by the system administrator</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/balanceactionresultingcalendar.jpg"
						format="JPG" scale="47"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Resulting calendar</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>The warning message on the calendar has changed to a simple
					notification/reminder, and the requested leave blocks change to "Approved"
						status.<note>The forfeiture and amount transfered amounts have been adjusted
						with respect to the transfer amount.</note></caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</section>
	</section>
 -->
	<section>
		<title>System Scheduled Time Off</title>
		<para>KHR Leave Management supports University Holiday designation via System Scheduled Time
			Off (SSTO). KHR's accrual service accrue the System Scheduled Time Off dates assocated
			with an employee's Leave Plan and Accrual Categories. </para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="../images/lm21/sstomaintdoc.png" format="png" scale="50"/>
			</imageobject>
			<caption>
				<para>The System Scheduled Time Off Maintenance Document.</para>
			</caption>
		</mediaobject>
		<tip>
			<para>Leave Plans that give employee's paid time off for holiday's will need to create
				an accrual category and default earn code before entered System Scheduled Time Off
				records for the Leave Plan. </para>
		</tip>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>SSTO Fields :</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the scheduled time off record will go into effect</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>The earn code associated with the scheduled time off.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Read-only field, populated from the accrual category field of the
							given earn code.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
						<entry>Read-only field, populated from the leave plan field of the given
							earn code / accrual category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrued Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the holiday is available to use. The accrual service will place
							a System Scheduled Time Off accrual leave block on the employees leave
							calendar on this date.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Scheduled Time Off Date</entry>
						<entry>Date of the scheduled time off that is put on the calendar. If there
							is Scheduled Time Off Date, then the accrual service will create a usage
							leave block on this date. If no Scheduled Time Off Date, then the
							employee will have an available balance as of the accrual date (i.e.
							floating holiday).</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Location</entry>
						<entry>The location in which this SSTO is applicable. Accepts wild card
							(%).</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the scheduled time off.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Amount of Time</entry>
						<entry>The amount of leave time available for this scheduled time off.
							Precision is based off Earn Code's Fractional Time Allowed
							field.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Unused Time</entry>
						<entry>Provides options on how the amount of time can be used. No Unused
							Time Allowed, Transfer and Bank. If an employee is allowed to transfer
							or bank time the accrued usage leave block will display on the leave
							calendar or timesheet with the option to remove the leave block to have
							the time transferred or banked. </entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Transfer to Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>If Unused Time is Transfer, the converted amount of time will be made
							available for use by this earn code.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Transfer Conversion Factor</entry>
						<entry>Conversion rate applied to the unused Amount of Time to be
							transferred</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Premium Holiday</entry>
						<entry>Flag indicating whether this SSTO is a premium holiday. If checked,
							'Y', gives certain employees a higher rate of pay when working the
							Scheduled Time Off Date.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Premium Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>Regular hours recorded on this date for non-Exempt employee's with
							this SSTO will receive the premium earn code for time worked. This earn
							code may have inflate factor.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Flag indicating activitiy. If checked, 'Y', record will be active as
							of the effective date. if unchecked, 'N', record will become inactive as
							of the effective date.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<!--
		<section>
			<title>Floating Holiday Configuration</title>
			<para>This example will move through basic configuration of system scheduled time
					off.
				<note><para>System Scheduled Time Off requires use of an Earn Code from which some
					of its properties are derived. For instruction on Earn Code configuration, see
					the chapter "Basic Configuration"</para>
				</note>
			</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Navigate to the System Scheduled Time Off Lookup via the link provided in
						the Leave Managment section of the Maintenance Tab.</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstolink.jpg" format="JPG" scale="50"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>The Create New Button</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Within the System Scheduled Time Off Lookup View, click <inlinemediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="../images/createnewbutton.jpg" format="JPG"
									scale="50"/>
							</imageobject>
							<textobject>
								<phrase>create new</phrase>
							</textobject>
						</inlinemediaobject>, located: </para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstocreatenew.jpg" format="JPG"
								scale="50"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>The Create New Button</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Within the Document Overview tab of the System Scheduled Time Off
						Maintenance Document, enter the required description.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Select an effective date from the current date up to one year in the
						future.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Enter or use the quick finder to return an earn code for the Earn Code
						field.</para>
					<note> When using the quick finder, the earn code returned will auto-populate
						the Accrual Category and Leave Plan fields from the values defined on that
						Earn Code. </note>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Select the Accrued Date.</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstoearncode.jpg" format="JPG"
								scale="45"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>System Scheduled Time Off accrued date defined</phrase>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<note>The accrued date should be the date that the Amount of Time for this SSTO
						is accumulated.</note>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>No Scheduled Time Off Date is required for floating holiday</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Enter the Location or use the quick finder to return a location.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Enter a description.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Enter the Amount of Time that can be taken for the scheduled time
						off.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Select "Bank" for Unused Time.</para>
					<note>Refer to the field summary at the start of this section for field
						requirements when selecting the Unused time. A value of "Bank" indicates the
						Amount of Time will be placed into the Accrual Category on the supplied
						Accrued Date. "Transfer" indicates the Amount of Time, adjusted by the
						Transfer Conversion Factor, will be available for transfer once the holiday
						accrual appears on the employees calendar. "No Unused Time Allowed" will
						generate a leave block on the calendar that cannot be removed or edited by
						the employee. If No Unused Time Allowed is selected, specify the same date
						for Scheduled Time Off Date and Accrued Date.</note>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Select whether this System Scheduled Time off is a premium holiday. A
						"Yes" indicates a higher rate of pay for employees who work this day.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Ensure that the "Active" box is checked</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstocomplete.jpg" format="JPG"
								scale="45"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>Completed System Scheduled Time Off Maintenance
								Document</phrase>
						</textobject>
						<caption>A Basic System Scheduled Time Off Maintenance Document</caption>
					</mediaobject>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Finally, Submit the document.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>The resulting accrual leave block generated by the floating holiday SSTO
				definition will appear on the employee's calendar as shown:</para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstobank1.jpg" format="JPG" scale="45"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Accrual generated when "Bank" is option selected as Unused
						Time.</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>A single accrual will be generated for SSTO's when "Bank" is selected for
					Unused Time option.</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<para>The following images show an SSTO defined with "No Unused Time Allowed", and the
				resulting leave blocks on an employees calendar.</para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstounuseddef.jpg" format="JPG" scale="45"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Example SSTO definition with "No Unused Time Allowed".</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>A sample SSTO definition with No Unused Time Allowed</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstounusedblock.jpg" format="JPG" scale="45"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Resulting leave blocks generated by the SSTO on the accrued/scheduled
						time off date.</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>No Unused Time Allowed creates one accrual leave block and one usage leave
					block on the employees calendar.</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</section>
-->
		<!--		<section>
			<title>Transferable System Scheduled Time Off</title>
			<para>This section will move through the steps required by employees in order for them
				to transfer unused time. We begin with a sample SSTO definition.</para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstotransferdef.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>Example SSTO definition that allows for the transfer of unused
						time.</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>A sample transferable SSTO</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<para>This SSTO results in the following leave blocks on the employees calendar:</para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstotransfer1.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>One accrual leave block is created on the accrued date, with the usage
						leave block created on the scheduled time off date.</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>Resulting leave blocks created by the above transferable SSTO
					definition.</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<para>To initiate the transfer the unused time, employees must:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Click the x on the usage leave block.</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstotransfer4.jpg" format="JPG"
								scale="60"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>Deleting the usage leave block created by the transferable SSTO
								will trigger the transfer of unused time</phrase>
						</textobject>
						<caption>The usage leave block generated by the transferable SSTO, when
							removed, triggers the balance transfer document.</caption>
					</mediaobject>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>In the dialog box that appears, confirm the deletion of the usage leave
						block.</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstotransfer2.jpg" format="JPG"
								scale="75"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>Deleting the usage leave block created by the transferable SSTO
								will trigger the transfer of unused time</phrase>
						</textobject>
						<caption>Employees must first confirm the removal of the usage leave block
							in order to be presented with the transfer document.</caption>
					</mediaobject>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstotransfer3.jpg" format="JPG"
								scale="45"/>
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<phrase>The balance transfer document resulting from the confirmation of
								usage leave block removal on a transferable SSTO</phrase>
						</textobject>
						<caption>The balance transfer document is pre-populated with values defined
							in the transferable SSTO at the start of this example.</caption>
					</mediaobject>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Finally, submit the balance transfer document</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>Upon successful submission of the Balance Transfer document, both leave blocks
				generated by the transferable SSTO are replaced with a single leave block
				representing the transaction that has taken place.</para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../images/lm/sstotransfer5.jpg" format="JPG" scale="45"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase>The resulting leave block generated by the transfer of unused time for
						the SSTO defined at the start of this section.</phrase>
				</textobject>
				<caption>A single leave block replaces the SSTO generated leave blocks. This leave
					block remains in requested status until the balance transfer document is
					approved or disapproved.</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<note>If the balance transfer document is disapproved, the system retro-actively adds
				the SSTO generated leave blocks back to the calendar.</note>
		</section>
-->
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Leave Blocks and Earn Codes</title>
		<para> Leave blocks are placed on leave calendars to show accruals, usage and adjustments of
			leave through out the reporting period. The type of leave block along with the earn code
			determine how the leave balances are calculated. </para>
		<section>
			<title>Leave Block Types</title>
			<para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Usage Leave Blocks: usage on Leave Calendar or Timesheet</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Accrual: leave blocks generated by the Accrual Service</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Balance Transfer: leave block created from Balance Transfer
							document</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Payout: leave block created from Payout document</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Carryover Adjustment: leave block created from Maximum Annual
							Carryover transaction</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Leave Adjustment: leave blocks created from Leave Adjustment
							document</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Donation: leave blocks created from Leave Donation document</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Leave Earn Codes</title>
			<para>All leave blocks on a leave calendar will have an Earn Code associated with it and
				the earn codes are associated with the employee's leave plan. The earn code's leave
				attributes, such as leave plan, defines the availablity of earn codes on the leave
				calendar and the impact the leave block has on the Accrual Category's balances.
			</para>
			<section>
				<title>Available Earn Codes for Leave</title>
				<para>Earn Codes that are available for reporting leave on an employee's leave calendar or timesheet
					is driven by the leave attributes of the earn code (See Earn Code maintenance document) and Earn Code Security record for the earn code.
					<orderedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>All earn codes for user's Leave Plan (Principal HR Attribute) and Accrual Balance Action is Usage</para>
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>Earn Code's with Allow Scheduled Leave are available on future leave reporting calendars. </para>
								</listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Earn Code Security record for the earn code determines if earn code is available on leave calendar and/or timesheet
								the roles that have permission to use the earn code.  
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Earn Codes flagged as FMLA or Worker's Comp are available on leave calendars and/or timesheets of employees have 
								FMLA and Worker's Comp indicators (Principal HR Attributes).   
							</para>
						</listitem>
						
					</orderedlist>
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title>Calculating Accrual Category Balances</title>
				<para>The leave summary provides the balances for leave on current and future leave calendars.  Year to Date (YTD) calculations
					uses the employee's Leave Plan calendar start date.  The earn code's Accrual Balance Action attribute will determine how the 
					leave block impacts how the leave earned and leave usage balances are calculated.  
				</para>
				<para>YTD Earned calculates all the sum of all the accrual, balance transer, payout,
					donation, and the carryover adjustement (previous years leave balanced created via batch job) leave block types.  This total also includes 
					any leave blocks from the time calendar, leave calendar and leave adjustments that have an earn code with Accrual Balance Action of Adjustment.  
				</para>
				<para>YTD Usage is calculation of all the approved time calendar, leave calendar, and leave adjustment leave blocks with earn codes that have an Accrual 
					Balance Action of Usage
				</para>
				<para>Planned/Future Usage calculation includes all approved, requested, and planned leave blocks that are on future leave calendar and have an 
					earn code with an Accrual Balance Action of Usage.  
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
