<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="approverOptions" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Approver Options</title>
    <para>This section discusses the key tasks that Approvers can perform in the KPME system, such
        as approving timesheets, entering/modifying Time Blocks, reviewing missed clock punches,
        adding Notes to a timesheet, or viewing Route Logs. KPME can have two types of approvers
        depending on the employee’s assignments on their timesheet or leave calendar. First required
        approval will be by the assignments Work Area approver. An optional second level routing can
        be designated by Department for approval of a department’s Payroll Processor. Work Area
        Approvers and Department Payroll Processors will use the same Time and Leave Approval tabs
        for approving timesheets and leave calendars. </para>
    <section>
        <title>Overview of the Time and Leave Approval tabs</title>
        <para>When you log into the system as an a work area approver or department payroll
            processor, you will have the Time Approval and Leave Approval tabs. Time Approval is
            used for approving their non- exempt employees’ timesheets. Leave Approval is used for
            approving exempt employees leave calendars. Work Area approvers can also access the
            Leave Request Approval page from the Leave Calendar to approve employee submitted leave
            requests. </para>
        <para>The approval tabs open the ‘ monitor and approval ’ page which provides a “one - stop”
            portal for approvers to monitor, clean-up and approve timesheets or leave calendars. The
            Calendar Period heading on these tabs will show what period you are in. </para>
        <para>This page provides the ability to ‘ sort and filter ’ by Department and Work Area to
            find those timesheets or leave calendars which you monitor and approve, and the ability
            to ‘ search by ’ Principal ID or Document ID and find a specific timesheet or leave
            calendar. However, these fields only search within the calendar period you are viewing
            at that time. </para>
        <para>It also provides two other dropdown search fields, Calendar Year and Calendar
            Pay/Leave Period when used jointly gives you the ability to instantly jump to any set of
            employee timesheets or leave calendars. </para>
        <para>Once you go to any historical timesheets or leave calendar, the Go to Current Period
            link will appear, and serves as a “shortcut” you can click to return to the same set of
            employee timesheets or leave calendars in the current calendar period. </para>
        <para>Finally, there are Previous and Next arrow buttons located on each side of the
            Calendar Period heading that allow you to scroll back and forth through a set of
            historical (or current) calendars by calendar period, in sequential order. </para>
        <para>You can open ‘quick views’ of any Notes and Warnings present on the timesheet or leave
            calendar, and scroll back and forth by calendar period to view and open previously
            “approved” timesheets and previous or future leave calendars. On Time Approval, you can
            monitor a Clock-Entry employee’s work status (in real -time). If one of your timesheet
            employees fails to clock out after 12 hours, their Name is shaded in red to flat it for
            attention. </para>
        <para>When necessary, you can click on a Document Id number to open that employee’s
            timesheet or leave calendar to enter corrections, to delete an automatic meal deduction
            on a timesheet when the employee did not take one, and if applicable, to distribute work
            hours between multiple Assignments. </para>
        <para>Additionally, you can open any historical timesheet or leave calendar to review the
            recorded time or leave blocks for that employee. </para>
        <para>Or, you can use the Name link to access the Person Info tab and view the jobs,
            assignments and KPME roles held by that employee. </para>
        <para>On Time Approval, a summary view of the employee’s timesheet can be viewed by using
            the Plus buttons to pop - open the summary (minus to close). This view can be used to
            monitory their daily hours, review their daily weekly and total pay period hours by
            assignment. Leave Approval has Plus buttons that expand to show the leave usage and
            balance for the period. </para>
        <para>These approval tools allow you to monitor, review and clean- up your employee’s
            timesheets or leave calendar prior to approval and during the calendar reporting period. </para>
        <para>If you are a work area approver, you should check your Action List notification emails
            during each pay period to ‘Approve’ or to ‘Correct and Approve’ any Missed Punch
            documents routed to you. These documents inform you of any missed clock-ins or
            clock-outs by the employees you supervise, and allow you to correct a document submitted
            with an inaccurate clock time. Leave requests are also routed to only the Work Area
            Approvers. Balance Transfers and Payouts triggered by max balances on the leave calendar
            are routed for approval to the work area approver and department’s payroll processor, if
            applicable for that department, </para>
        <para>At the end of each pay period, work area approvers must approve timesheets. The
            ‘monitor and approval’ page provides you the option to approve an individual timesheet
            or do bulk approvals. Work area timesheets that require the second level Department
            Payroll Processor approval will be routed for approval. On ‘monitor and approval’ page,
            timesheets that enroute will have a label above the “Approve” button to indicate the
            next approval action, “Approver” or “Payroll Processor” , The information on a fully
            approved (Final) timesheet is then processed and can be sent to an associated Payroll
            system. </para>
        <para>After the leave calendar period, an exempt employee can submit their leave calendars
            for approval. On the Leave Approval page, employees’ leave calendar will be available to
            approve individual or in bulk. </para>
        <para>The following illustration of the Time Approval tab demonstrates the options available
            on both the approval tabs. </para>
        <para>(The letters located next to each option below are used to show that option on the
            illustration.) </para>
        <para>Let’s look’s at the options available to you on the Time Approval tab. You can: </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Timesheet Monitoring, Reviewing and Correcting</title>
        <section>
            <title>Finding Timesheets</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Viewing Previous and Next Timesheets</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Viewing Employee Work Status</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Viewing Timesheet Warnings and Notes</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Opening (and Closing) the 'Summary View' of Employee Hours</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Opening a Timsheet</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding Time Blocks to a Timesheet</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Editing Existing Time Blocks</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Deleting Time Blocks</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adjusting Shift Differential Hours</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Timesheet Approval and Routing</title>
        <section>
            <title>Employee Submission</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Approver Approvals</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Timesheets Not Ready to Approve</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Approving Timesheets</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Automated Approvals</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding a Note to Employee Timesheets</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Checking the Route Log</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Leave Calendar Monitoring, Reviewing and Correcting</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Leave Reqeuest Approval</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Leave Calendar Approval and Routing</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
</chapter>
