<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="employeeOptions" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Employee Options</title>
    <para>This section provides a description of the timesheet and leave calendar used in KPME, including the navigational options. 
        In addition, it describes the two methods used to record work or leave hours, explains how to use the timesheet to record 
        hours, distribute work hours and report missed clock punches, and how to request future leave.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Timesheets</title>
        <para>Non-exempt employee in KPME has one timesheet for each pay period. Pay periods can be set up to fit departmental needs, 
            such as weekly, biweekly, or bimonthly. Each FSLA (Fair Labor Standards Act) period meets the standard for overtime hours, 
            overtime pay and collected unpaid overtime. Each timesheet represents a document in the Kuali Rice/Workflow system—a 
            routing and approval engine used to manage who can view and take actions on a particular timesheet.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Timesheet Creation</title>
            <para>Employees with active KPME assignments during the pay period will have timesheets created automatically before the 
                next pay period begins, or when the batch job is scheduled. The batch job can be run nightly.</para>
            <para>If an employee is missing a timesheet, one may need to be created by the System Administrator who can use the 
                timesheet Create maintenance document to do so. Please contact your Department Administrator or System Administrator 
                and include the employee’s Principal ID number in the request.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Clock-Entry vs. Manual Entry</title>
            <para>There are two methods an employee may use to record regular hours:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Clock-Entry</emphasis> is used when capturing exact
                        in and out times. After logging in, the timesheet opens on the <emphasis
                            role="bold">Clock Tab</emphasis>. This tab includes a clock section with
                        a dropdown list of active Clock Assignments, and one selects the appropriate
                        assignment to clock in or out. Clock buttons that may be visible here
                        include Clock In or Clock Out, Missed Punch and Distribute Time
                        Blocks.</para>
                    <para>Only assignments where you must clock in and out will show up in the Clock
                        Assignment dropdown. If you also have Manual Entry assignments you will need
                        to click on the <emphasis role="bold">Time Detail</emphasis> tab to manually
                        enter those work hours (see Manual Entry below).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Manual Entry</emphasis> is used when clocking in/out
                        is not required, and the hours worked are recorded by entering blocks of
                        time manually into the timesheet. After logging in, the timesheet opens on
                        the <emphasis role="bold">Time Detail</emphasis> tab. Manual Entry
                        assignments do not appear on the Clock Tab. If your only time assignment is
                        a Manual Entry assignment, you will not see the Clock Tab on your
                        timesheet.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Timesheet Overview and Navigation</title>
            <para>When you open a timesheet, it shows side by side <emphasis role="bold">Navigation
                    tabs</emphasis> that you can use to navigate from page to page. These tabs show
                where you are and where you can go within the timesheet.</para>
            <para>To navigate to any other page in your timesheet, just click on that tab.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you are an employee with a <emphasis role="bold">Clock-Entry</emphasis>
                        assignment, your timesheet will open on the Clock tab so you can easily
                        clock in and out. This tab also provides a <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Note</emphasis> section, so you can add a note to your timesheet. (See
                            <emphasis role="italic">Clock</emphasis> tab illustration below.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you are an employee with a <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Manual-Entry</emphasis> assignment, your timesheet will open on the
                        Time Detail tab, where you manually add the time blocks you have worked or
                        the leave hours you have taken.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Other navigational tabs you may see on your timesheet include the <emphasis
                    role="italic">Time Detail</emphasis> tab, the <emphasis role="italic">Leave
                    Calendar</emphasis> tab,<emphasis role="italic"> Person Info</emphasis> tab and
                the <emphasis role="underline">Help tab</emphasis>. If you are an employee who is
                also an approver for a Work Area, you may also see a <emphasis role="italic">Time
                    Approva</emphasis>l and/or a<emphasis role="italic"> Leave Approval</emphasis>
                tabs.</para>
            <para>All timesheets display a “<emphasis role="bold">Document Header</emphasis>” in the
                top right corner that includes your identifying information, such as Employee Name,
                Employee Id, (timesheet) Document Id, and Document status (Saved, Enroute, or
                Final).</para>
            <para>This area also includes a <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline"
                        >Logout</emphasis></emphasis> link that you will use to log out of the
                system and close your timesheet.</para>
            <para>If you click on your underlined Employee Name here, it will open the Person Info tab, where you can view details
                about your time assignments, jobs, and roles. Or you can click on the Person Info tab to open the same page.</para>
            <para>Let’s take a closer look at the<emphasis role="italic"> Time Detail</emphasis>
                tab. (See<emphasis role="italic"> Time Detail</emphasis> tab illustration
                below.)</para>
            <para>All employees (whether <emphasis role="bold">Clock-Entry</emphasis> or<emphasis
                    role="bold"> Manual-Entry</emphasis>) will have the <emphasis role="italic">Time
                    Detail</emphasis> tab which opens a calendar view of the pay period covered by
                the timesheet. (A pay period can be weekly, biweekly, bimonthly or monthly,
                depending how your organization wishes to define it.) </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Clock-Entry</emphasis> employees will use this tab to review
                the time blocks they have clocked on the timesheet and to manually enter any leave
                hours, such as sick, vacation or PTO they took during the pay period. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Manual-Entry</emphasis> employees will use this tab to
                manually add time blocks for the hours they have worked and the leave hours they
                have taken during the pay period. </para>
            <para>There are <emphasis role="bold">Previous</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Next</emphasis> arrow buttons located on each side of the Pay Period heading
                that allows you to scroll back and forth by pay period, in chronological order, and
                view a previously approved timesheet or to go forward to the next timesheet (in the
                order). </para>
            <para>This tab also provides two dropdown search fields, <emphasis role="bold">Calendar
                    Year</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Pay Period</emphasis> where if you
                jointly select the year and pay period, it jumps to the selected timesheet, so you
                can view it. </para>
            <para>Once you open any previous timesheet, the<emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                        role="underline"> Go to Current Period</emphasis></emphasis> link will
                appear on the page, and serves as a “shortcut” you can click to return to your
                timesheet for the current pay period. </para>
            <para>Also, <emphasis role="bold">Clock-Entry</emphasis> employees can click the
                    <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Actual Time
                    inquiry</emphasis></emphasis> link to view a list of their actual clock times. </para>
            <para>Below the calendar is a <emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis> section that
                shows the total Worked Hours for each day along with a breakdown of the hours worked
                by assignment, day and by earn code (regular, vacation, sick, overtime, shift,
                etc.). It also provides a Weekly and Period Total. </para>
            <para>An Earn Code is a classification of earning that represents the hours worked or
                some special earning like shift time, sick time or overtime. An Assignment is a
                unique combination of your Job, Job Number, and Work Area (and Task), and is used to
                record the hours that you work. </para>
            <para>The bottom of the timesheet on both the <emphasis role="italic">Clock</emphasis>
                and <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail</emphasis> tab contains a <emphasis
                    role="bold">Note</emphasis> section, which allows you, your approvers and
                administrators to add and save notes on the timesheet. The <emphasis role="italic"
                    >Time Detail</emphasis> tab also includes a <emphasis role="bold">Route
                    Log</emphasis> section that allows you to view the approval routing for your
                timesheet. </para>
            <para>If you click on the<emphasis role="italic"> Leave Calendar tab</emphasis>, you see
                leave recorded on the timesheet. When you scroll forward to future calendars, leave
                blocks can be added similar to time detail that will be used to plan and request
                time off. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Clock-Entry Timekeeping</title>
        <para>Employees with <emphasis role="bold">Clock-Entry</emphasis> assignments use the
                <emphasis role="italic">Clock</emphasis> tab to clock in and out. When you login to
            KPME Time, your timesheet will open on this tab. </para>
        <para>Let’s review the fields and buttons available on this tab:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The “ <emphasis role="underline">Current Time</emphasis> ” field shows you the
                    current clock time. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The “ <emphasis role="underline">Work Status</emphasis> ” field shows you the
                    last clock action you recorded on your timesheet. It shows your last action
                    (clocked in/clocked out), and the date and time of that action. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>A time <emphasis role="bold">Assignment</emphasis> is a unique combination of
                    your Job, Job Number, Work Area (and Task), and is used to record the hours that
                    you work. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The “ <emphasis role="underline">Clock Assignment</emphasis>” field will show
                    you a list of your current assignments so you can select the specific <emphasis
                        role="bold">Assignment</emphasis> you are going to clock in on. If you only
                    have one assignment, or are already clocked in there wo n’ t be an assignment
                    dropdown. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Clock
                        In</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                            role="underline">Clock Out </emphasis></emphasis>buttons allow you to
                    clock in or out.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you forgot to clock in or clock out, the <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis
                            role="underline">Missed Punch</emphasis></emphasis> button allows you to
                    submit a missed punch document to notify your approver or supervisor and record
                    the “missed punch” on your timesheet.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The optional <emphasis role="bold">Distribute Time Blocks</emphasis> button,
                    when present, allows you to clock in and out of a single assignment to create
                    one time block and then distribute those hours at the end of your shift to
                    multiple assignments. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis> section allows you to add a Note on
                    your timesheet.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Logout</emphasis> link (located with the “<emphasis
                        role="bold">Document Header</emphasis>” in the upper-right hand corner of
                    the page) allows you to log out of the system and close your timesheet.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <section>
            <title>How to Record Hours (on the Clock tab)</title>
            <para>On the <emphasis role="italic">Clock</emphasis> tab, you will use the
                clock-buttons to clock in and out. This tab also allows you to submit a Missed Punch
                document if you missed a clock in, lunch out, lunch in, or clock out; to add a Note
                to your timesheet; and (if applicable) to distribute work hours clocked on one
                assignment over several assignments. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Clocking In and Out</title>
            <para>To clock in: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Log into KPME Time. (Timesheet opens on the <emphasis role="italic"
                            >Clock</emphasis> tab.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the<emphasis role="underline"> Clock Assignment</emphasis> field,
                        select an Assignment. (If you only have one assignment, it will already be
                        selected.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click on <emphasis role="bold">Clock In</emphasis> button. (Work Status
                        will show you are clocked in.)</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>To clock out: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Log into KPME Time and click on<emphasis role="bold"> Clock Out</emphasis>
                        button. (Work Status will then change to show you are clocked out.)</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding a Missed Punch</title>
            <para>If you missed your last clock action, you can click on the <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Missed Punch</emphasis> button to add that missed clock in, lunch out, return
                from lunch, or clock out to your timesheet. </para>
            <para>This opens the <emphasis role="italic">Missed Punch</emphasis> maintenance
                document, where you enter your missing clock action information and submit it for
                approval. </para>
            <para>Once you submit this document, the missed clock action is added to your timesheet,
                and the missed punch document is routed to your timesheet approver for approval. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Only submit a Missed Punch
                        document if you missed your last clock action .
                </emphasis></emphasis></para>
            <warning><para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Employees can only submit one Missed Punch
                            document per (work shift) Time Block.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
            </warning>
            <para>To submit this document, please follow the steps below:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>From the Clock tab, click on <emphasis role="bold">Missed
                        Punch</emphasis>. This opens the Missed Punch maintenance document (and
                        inserts your timesheet Document ID and your Principal ID).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the Assignment where you missed clocking in or out. (If you only have one Assignment, the field
                        will default to that value.)</para>
                    <note><para>Note: The<emphasis role="underline"> Missed Clock Action</emphasis> field will default to the
                            clock punch that you missed, (i.e., ‘clock out’ if you missed clocking
                            out, or ‘lunch in’ if you missed clocking your return from
                            lunch).</para></note>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Enter the date of your missed clock punch into the<emphasis
                            role="underline"> Missed Action Date</emphasis> field. The Date format
                        to use is: MM/DD/YYYY. You can type in the date or select it using the
                        calendar button, located with each date field.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Enter the time (then enter a space followed by AM or PM) of your missed
                        clock punch into the<emphasis role="underline"> Missed Action
                            Time</emphasis> field. The format to use is: <emphasis role="bold">hh:mm
                            AM/PM (i.e., 10:54 AM or 9:06 PM)</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Submit</emphasis> to enter the missed punch on
                        your timesheet.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Close</emphasis> to close out of the
                        document.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Time Detail Tab</title>
            <para>The <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail </emphasis>tab is visible to all
                employees. As a <emphasis role="bold">Clock-Entry</emphasis> employee, you will use
                this tab to view the time blocks clocked on your timesheet, to add time blocks that
                record any leave hours you are taking, and to correct (the assignment for) a time
                block that was accidently clocked on the wrong assignment. </para>
            <para>You can also use this tab to view a summary of your worked hours, to add a
                timesheet Note, to view the Route Log to see who approves your timesheet, and, if
                applicable, to view any automatic meal deductions that were subtracted. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding Leave Hours to a Timesheet</title>
            <para>Any employee (whether <emphasis role="bold">Clock-Entry</emphasis> or <emphasis
                    role="bold">Manual-Entry</emphasis> ) who qualifies to accrue benefit Leave
                Hours such as paid time-off (PTO), vacation (VAC) or sick hours (SCK) will use the
                    <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail </emphasis>tab to enter those hours for the
                current pay period. Future leave hours can be requested from the Leave Calendar tab
                reviewed later in this section. </para>
            <para>This requires that you enter the number of “ hours ” to track your usage . Once
                the appropriate benefit earn code is selected, the ‘Add Time Blocks’ entry box w ill
                change to display an ‘Hours’ input field (instead of the usual In/Out fields. </para>
            <para>To enter leave hours on your timesheet: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Log into KPME Time (and go to the <emphasis role="italic">Time
                            Detail</emphasis> tab.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On the timesheet pay period calendar, select the day or date range on which you want to add leave
                        hours. This will open the ‘Add Time Blocks’ entry box:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>To add leave hours for one single day, click on the day you want to add.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>To add the same number of leave hours on multiple days, go to the
                                first day you are taking leave in the calendar, and simultaneously
                                    <emphasis role="bold">click and hold down your (left) mouse
                                    button</emphasis> and drag the cursor across the days you will
                                be out, and then release the button. (For example, click and hold on
                                Monday, drag cursor across to Friday, and release it, and that will
                                enter a date range of Monday through Friday.)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>You can also type in or select a range of dates in the <emphasis
                                    role="underline">Date Range</emphasis> fields on the ‘Add Time
                                Blocks’ entry box to enter the same number of leave hours on each
                                day. If you type in the dates, use this format: M/D/YYYY (e.g.
                                2/4/2012 or 10/22/2012 )</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the <emphasis role="underline">Earn Code</emphasis> for the type of
                        leave you are taking, such as SCK (sick), PTO, VAC (vacation), etc.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the <emphasis role="underline">Hours</emphasis> field, enter the number
                        of leave hours you are taking.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you selected a range of dates, make sure the ‘Apply time to each day’ checkbox is checked, so the
                        hours you entered are applied to each day.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> and verify that the time
                        block(s) for your leave hours are correct on your timesheet.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Editing Leave Hours on a Timesheet</title>
            <para>To <emphasis role="bold">edit</emphasis> a leave time block: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click on the underlined Assignment name (in the example shown above, you
                        would click on ‘<emphasis role="underline">Cust Serv
                        Desk</emphasis>’).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>This reopens the ‘Add Time Blocks’ entry box and you can modify the
                            <emphasis role="underline">Date Range</emphasis>, the <emphasis
                            role="underline">Earn Code</emphasis> (VAC, PTO, SCK, CPT, etc.) or the
                        number of <emphasis role="underline">Hours</emphasis> of leave you are
                        taking.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When finished, click <emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis> and verify
                        that the time block(s) are correct on your timesheet.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Deleting Leave Hours from a Timesheet</title>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To <emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis> a leave time block from a
                        timesheet, click on the red ‘X’ button, in the upper right-hand corner of
                        the time block. (See Leave time block example above).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When asked to confirm the deletion, click <emphasis role="bold"
                            >OK</emphasis> to delete it.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Correcting a Time Block Clocked on the Wrong Job/Assignment</title>
            <para>If you clock in on one job assignment, and find that you have clocked-in on the
                wrong assignment, you should continue to work and clock out at the end of your work
                period. That will record a Time Block for that assignment. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">During the current pay period
                        only</emphasis></emphasis>, you can change the assignment for a Time Block
                you clocked and recorded under the wrong assignment so it shows for the assignment
                you actually worked. </para>
            <para>To move a clocked Time Block (and the hours worked) over to the correct
                Assignment: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Go to the <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail</emphasis> tab on your
                        timesheet.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Find the time block you need to change.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click on the underlined <emphasis role="underline">Assignment</emphasis>
                        link in that time block (which opens the ‘Add Time Block’ entry box).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the <emphasis role="underline">Assignment</emphasis> dropdown, select
                        the assignment that you actually worked.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Update</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>This will update your timesheet so that Time Block (and the work hours) will show
                under the Assignment that you actually worked. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Viewing Recorded Time Blocks on your Pay Period Calendar</title>
            <para>Click on the <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail</emphasis> tab to open the Pay
                Period calendar and view the current pay period. (See the illustration of the Calen
                dar under the section, “ <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Timesheet
                        Overview and Navigation </emphasis></emphasis>.”) </para>
            <para>This tab displays all the time blocks you have clocked, or manually entered, such
                as time blocks you added to record any leave hours that you took during the pay
                period. If you work more than one time assignment; they are color coded, so you can
                see the time blocks and hours that you have accumulated under each assignment. </para>
            <para>There are <emphasis role="bold">Previous</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Next</emphasis> buttons next to the pay period dates, that allow you to scroll
                back and forth to view your previous timesheets. A <emphasis role="bold">Document
                    Header</emphasis> includes your Name, Employee Id, and the Document Id </para>
            <para>of the timesheet. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Viewing a Summary of Worked Hours</title>
            <para>Below the calendar is a section showing a <emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis>
                of the hours that you have recorded on your timesheet. This section shows you the
                total ‘Worked Hours’ for each day along with a breakdown of the hours you worked by
                assignment, day and by earn code (regular, vacation, sick, overtime, shift, etc.).
                It also provides a weekly total, FLSA total and period total. </para>
            <para>An earn code is a classification of earnings that represents regular hours worked
                or special type of earnings like sick time, shift or premium pay. </para>
            <para>Regular hours that contribute toward weekly overtime eligibility are totaled and
                displayed. Sick or Vacation/PTO hours will also appear in separate rows. Overtime or
                Compensatory hours, if they exist, will appear in a row below your regular hours.
                Additional pay hours, such as shift rates or premiums will appear in rows above or
                below that. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Viewing (and Correcting) Automatic Lunch/Meal Deductions</title>
            <para>Some departments set up automatic lunch deduction rules for Clock-Entry employees.
                In those departments, all employees have to do is clock in and clock out (and work
                the required minimum number of hours), and the timesheet will automatically deduct
                the meal (whether breakfast, lunch, or dinner), usually 30 minutes (0.50 hours) or
                60 minutes (1 hour). </para>
            <para>Timesheets will show the amount of time deducted for a meal, highlighted in a
                yellow bar, at the bottom of a clocked time block. </para>
            <para>If an employee works through a scheduled meal or skips it for some reason, the
                timesheet may still show that a meal was deducted on that day. </para>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">If you are a Clock-Entry employee and work through or skip
                    your scheduled meal break (with departmental approval), and a meal was deducted
                    on that day, please notify your supervisor to correct your timesheet.</emphasis>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Distributing Work Hours</title>
            <para>Some employees will have the option to clock in and out of a single Assignment and
                then click on the<emphasis role="bold"> Distribute Time Blocks</emphasis> button (on
                the Clock tab) to distribute those worked hours between two or more assignments. </para>
            <note>
                <para>You can also open the Note section when working in these screens to add a note to your timesheet.</para>
            </note>
            <para>To distribute clocked work hours:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>From the Clock tab, click on <emphasis role="bold">Distribute Time
                            Blocks</emphasis>. This opens the <emphasis role="italic">Time Blocks to
                            Distribute</emphasis> screen.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the Time Block you want to distribute and click <emphasis
                            role="bold">Edit</emphasis> . This opens the<emphasis role="italic">
                            Distribute Hours </emphasis>screen, showing the Time Block you selected
                        with the total Hours you worked. </para>
                    <para>Just below your selected Time Block, a special “form” displays and shows
                        that Time Block as already split into two rows so you can enter Time Blocks
                        for each of those two different Assignments. </para>
                    <para>If you are distributing the hours from your original Time Block to more
                        than two Assignments, use the <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> button to
                        add additional (Assignment) rows to the form. Then, complete each row on the
                        form to enter the distinct Time Blocks you worked in each Assignment. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To complete the form and distribute your hours: </para>
                    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Determine how many Assignment rows you need on the form. You need one row on the form for 
                                each Assignment you actually worked. (To distribute hours to three Assignments, you need three 
                                rows; for four Assignments, four rows, and so on.)</para>
                            <para>To add an additional row to the form, click <emphasis role="bold"
                                    >Add</emphasis>, and repeat for each row you need to add. This
                                inserts a duplicate of the second row onto the form.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>On the form, go through every row and verify the Assignment
                                showing in each one is correct. Use the <emphasis role="underline"
                                    >Assignment</emphasis> dropdown in any row where you need to
                                change the Assignment to the one you actually worked.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Go through each row and verify the <emphasis role="underline"
                                    >Begin Date</emphasis> and<emphasis role="underline"> End
                                    Date</emphasis> are correct for the selected Assignment. To
                                change a date, click on the calendar button, and then select a date
                                from the pop-up calendar. Or, type a date into the field, formatted
                                as DD/MM/YYYY.</para>
                            <note>
                                <para>You probably won’t need to adjust these dates unless you worked a Time Block in that Assignment that 
                                    was overnight and spans over two days.</para>
                            </note>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Go through each row and enter your <emphasis role="underline"
                                    >Begin Time</emphasis> and <emphasis role="underline">End
                                    Time</emphasis> for the selected Assignment:</para>
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>In Row 1 all you can enter is your actual <emphasis
                                            role="underline">End Time</emphasis> for that
                                        Assignment. (The <emphasis role="underline">Begin
                                            Time</emphasis> cannot be changed.)</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Go to the next row on the form and enter the same
                                            <emphasis role="underline">Begin Time</emphasis> as the
                                            <emphasis role="underline">End Time</emphasis> you
                                        entered in the row above. Then continue (in that same row)
                                        and enter the <emphasis role="underline">End
                                        Time</emphasis>, Repeat this step for each row on the form,
                                            <emphasis role="bold">unless it is the last
                                            row</emphasis>.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para><emphasis role="bold">If this is the last row on the
                                            form,</emphasis> all you need to enter is the <emphasis
                                            role="underline">Begin Time</emphasis> (and leave the
                                            <emphasis role="underline">End Time</emphasis>
                                        unchanged).</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <para>The form will then show each Time Block and calculate the hours you worked in that Time Block for each 
                                Assignment.</para>
                            <note>
                                <para>Roll your cursor over the Question Mark, to see what formats are accepted by time-entry fields.</para>
                            </note>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Verify the <emphasis role="bold">Total Hours</emphasis> you
                                distributed to all your Assignments match the number of <emphasis
                                    role="bold">Hours</emphasis> you worked in the original Time
                                Block (at the top of the screen). If not, enter any adjustments to
                                the Time Blocks in your Assignment rows, as needed.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis>. That will distribute the
                        hours, and return you to the <emphasis role="italic">Clock</emphasis> tab.
                        If you open your <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail </emphasis>tab you can
                        view the new Time Blocks (and hours worked) under each Assignment.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Manual Entry Timekeeping</title>
        <para>Employees with <emphasis role="bold">Manual-Entry</emphasis> assignments will use the
                <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail</emphasis> tab to manually add time blocks for
            the hours they work or the hours of leave they take. When you login to KPME Time, your
            timesheet will open on this tab. </para>
        <section>
            <title>How to Record Hours (on the Time Detail tab)</title>
            <para>If you have a <emphasis role="bold">Manual-Entry</emphasis> assignment, you will
                use the <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail</emphasis> tab on your timesheet to
                record your work hours. Here you enter your time “In” and time “Out” which adds a
                Time Block to your timesheet. If you accrue benefit leave hours, you will also enter
                a Time Block to record the type of leave (sick, vacation, PTO) and number of “Hours”
                that you took. This tab also allows designated employees to add a Time Block to
                enter a fixed -rate dollar “Amount” (such as tips). </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Adding Time Blocks to a Timesheet</title>
            <para>To <emphasis role="bold">add</emphasis> work hours, leave hours, or fixed dollar
                amounts on your timesheet, you must add a Time Block: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Log into KPME Time. (Timesheet opens on the <emphasis role="italic">Time
                            Detail</emphasis> tab.)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On the pay period calendar, select the day or date range to add your Time Blocks:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>To add a Time Block for one single day, click on the day you want to add.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>To add the same Time Block on multiple days, such as Monday
                                through Friday, <emphasis role="bold">click and hold down the (left)
                                    mouse button</emphasis> on the first day of your date range
                                (Monday), <emphasis role="bold">and simultaneously drag the
                                    cursor</emphasis> over to the last day in the range (Friday),
                                then release it.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                    <para>If you select multiple days, it highlights those days, and the ‘Add Time Blocks’ 
                        entry box opens showing the range of dates you selected. A single day entry, just opens the 
                        ‘Add Time Blocks’ screen with the date range showing as the same day.</para>
                    <para>If you work an <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">overnight
                                shift</emphasis></emphasis>, you can use the <emphasis role="bold"
                            >click and drag</emphasis> method to select your two days. But, make
                        sure you UNCHECK the ‘Apply time to each day’ checkbox.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Once you open the ‘Add Time Blocks’ entry box, you can also type in the date range you want or
                                click the calendar button, located with each date field, to pop-up a monthly calendar and 
                                select a range of dates. For example, you could type in or select the date range as: 02/27/2012 
                                to 03/01/2012.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Verify the <emphasis role="underline">Date Range </emphasis>is
                        correct.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the <emphasis role="underline">Assignment</emphasis> for the time
                        block you are adding. (If you only have one Assignment, it will already be
                        selected.) A time <emphasis role="bold">Assignment</emphasis> is a unique
                        combination of your Job, Job Number, Work Area (and Task), and is used to
                        record the hours that you work.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Earn Code field will default to the regular earn code for your job
                        (RGH, RGW, RGN, RGP, or RBP). If you need to change it, select the
                        appropriate <emphasis role="underline">Earn Code</emphasis> from the
                        dropdown.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can enter Time Blocks for hours you have worked, hours of leave time, or for fixed dollar amounts:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If your entry is to add a time block for hours you have worked:</para>
                            <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>In the ‘<emphasis role="underline">In</emphasis>’ box,
                                        enter the time you started working.</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>In the ‘<emphasis role="underline">Out</emphasis>’ box,
                                        enter the time you stopped working</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </orderedlist>
                            <note>
                                <para>Roll your cursor over the Question Mark, to see what formats are accepted by time-entry fields.</para>
                            </note>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If your entry is to add a time block of Leave Hours (e.g., sick, vacation):</para>
                            <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>In the ‘<emphasis role="underline">Hours</emphasis>’ box,
                                        enter the number of leave hours you are taking.</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </orderedlist>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>If your entry is to add an amount (e.g. tips):</para>
                            <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>In the ‘<emphasis role="underline">Amount</emphasis>’ box,
                                        enter the fixed dollar amount (e.g. 29 or 100 or
                                        79.75).</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </orderedlist>
                        </listitem>                        
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When checked, the ‘Apply time to each day’ checkbox will enter the same
                        time blocks each day, for the range of dates you entered. <emphasis
                            role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Uncheck this box for overnight
                                shifts.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When finished, click <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis>. This adds a
                        time block either for the hours you worked, the leave hours or the fixed
                        amount you entered.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Editing Existing Time Blocks</title>
            <para>To <emphasis role="bold">edit</emphasis> a time block: </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click on the underlined Assignment name (in the example above, you would
                        click on ‘<emphasis role="underline">Cust Serv Desk</emphasis>’).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>This reopens the ‘Add Time Blocks’ entry box and you can edit the
                            <emphasis role="underline">Date Range</emphasis>, and/or the<emphasis
                            role="underline"> Earn Code</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Depending on the Earn Code selected, you can also edit the <emphasis
                            role="underline">In</emphasis> and <emphasis role="underline"
                            >Out</emphasis> times, the number of <emphasis role="underline"
                            >Hours</emphasis>, or the <emphasis role="underline"
                        >Amount</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When finished with your entries, click <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Update</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Verify that the Time Blocks are correct before you exit the timesheet.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Deleting Time Blocks</title>
            <para>To <emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis> any time block from a timesheet, click
                on the red ‘X’ button, in the upper right-hand corner of the time block. (See Time
                Block examples above.) When asked to confirm the deletion, click <emphasis
                    role="bold">OK</emphasis> to delete it. </para>
            <para>Employees can continue to edit their timesheets until it is approved by their
                timesheet Approver. If you have any questions about which Assignments or Earn Codes
                you should use, please contact your Approver. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Viewing a Summary of Worked Hours</title>
            <para>On the <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail</emphasis> tab, below the calendar is a
                section showing a <emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis> of the hours that you
                have recorded on your timesheet. This section shows you the total ‘Worked Hours’ for
                each day along with a breakdown of the hours you worked by assignment, day and by
                earn code (regular, vacation, sick, overtime, shift, etc.). It also provides a week
                total, FLSA total, and period total. </para>
            <para>An earn code is a classification of earning that represents regular hours worked
                or special type of earning like sick time, shift or premium pay. </para>
            <para>Regular hours that contribute toward weekly overtime eligibility are totaled and
                displayed. Sick or Vacation hours will also appear in separate rows. Overtime or
                Compensatory hours, if they exist, will appear in a row below your regular hours.
                Additional pay hours, such as shift rates or premiums will appear in rows above or
                below that. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Timesheet Errors and Warnings</title>
        <para>If an employee should input an error when adding or modifying time blocks, the ‘Add
            Time Block’ entry box will show an error message highlighted in red at the top of the
            box. Corrective action should be taken to fix the fields noted in the error message. </para>
        <para>Possible entry errors include:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The time or date is not valid.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Start time and end time cannot be equivalent.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Time entry field cannot be empty.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Hour field cannot be empty.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Amount field cannot be empty</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Amount cannot have more than two digits after decimal point.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The start date/time is outside the pay period.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The end date/time is outside the pay period.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>One time block cannot exceed 24 hours.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The time block you are trying to add overlaps with an existing time block.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Assignment is not valid for start/end date</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail </emphasis>tab will also display error and
            warning messages at the top of the timesheet in red text. Most entries, such as using
            sick or vacation time in excess of available balances, will issue a warning.</para>
        <para>If there are only warnings, the timesheet will advance for approval, but the warning stays on the 
            timesheet so the Approver will see it during approvals.</para>
        <para>Corrective action should be taken to fix any errors or warnings that violate University or 
            departmental policies.</para>
        <para>The image below shows an example of a timesheet warning:</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
