<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="introduction" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section>
        <title>What is KPME?</title>
        <para>KPME is an open source, Comprehensive HR/Payroll system built for Higher Ed, By Higher
            Ed. The KPME roadmap can be found at: <link xlink:href="http://kuali.org/kpme">http://kuali.org/kpme</link>. 
            The first KPME module release was Time and Attendance and the latest release is Leave Management
            that includes integration with Time and Attendance. KPME modules handle multiple jobs,
            pay types, and pay cycles based on employee’s active appointment in your department. The
            system also provides approval routing based on jobs so your designated approvers can
            view and approve employee timesheets and leave online. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What is KPME TIime?</title>
        <para>KPME Time provides a 24/7 electronic timekeeping system to record hours worked, hours in pay status, 
            and absent time in an easy-to-use, always accessible, web-based interface. It also calculates all special 
            rates of pay such as overtime, shift differential, premium, and holiday pay.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What is KPME Leave Management?</title>
        <para>KPME Leave Management also provides a 24/7 electronic leave management system for organizations and their 
            employees to accrue, request, report and track the use of benefit time (eg. Vacation, Sick) for exempt and 
            non-exempt faculty and staff.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Why is is used?</title>
        <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>When is it used??</title>
        <para>KPME’s Timekeeping and Leave Management is available 24 hours, 7 days a week, and 365 days a year for 
            employees to record hours worked and report leave and for approvers to process timesheet approvals.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>How does it work?</title>
        <section>
            <title>Work Area Example</title>
            <para/>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Recommended System Specifications</title>
        <para>Note: These configurations are current as of the publication of this User Manual.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Desktop Devices</title>
            <para>Workstations must run Windows 7, XP or Vista with Internet Explorer version 5.5 Service Pack 2 or newer. 
                KPME also functions with other operating systems and browsers such as Mozilla Firefox and Google Chrome.</para>
        </section>
    </section>    
</chapter>
