<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="leaveCalendar" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Leave Calendar</title>
        <para>Leave eligible employees in KPME will have <emphasis role="italic">Leave
            Calendar</emphasis> tab that displays the leave reporting period for the employee. Leave
        reporting periods can be set up to fit department needs, such as weekly, biweekly, or
        bimonthly. </para>
        <para>Non-exempt employees will report their leave usage on their timesheet and will use
                future leave calendars to plan and request leave. Exempt employees will report leave
                on their current and previous reporting leave calendars and will use future leave
                calendar periods to plan and request leave. Exempt employees’ reporting leave
                calendars Kuali Rice/Workflow documents — Kuali Rice/Workflow is a routing and
                approval engine used to manage who can view and take actions on a particular leave
                calendar. Exempt employees with an active KPME Assignment will have a leave calendar
                automatically created when accessing the current leave calendar period. </para>
        <para>Navigating the <emphasis role="italic">Leave Calendar</emphasis> is similar to the
            <emphasis role="italic">Time Detail</emphasis> tab described earlier in this document.
        There are two additional leave related links next to the go to <emphasis role="underline"
            >Current Leave Calendar</emphasis> link. </para>
        <para><emphasis role="underline">Leave Ledger</emphasis> is a tabular version of all the
        leave blocks on the leave calendar showing planned, requested, usage, and accrual leave
        entries in chronological order with balances for identified accrual categories. Previous and
        future year leave usage and accruals can be accessed by using the scrolling buttons shown on
        each side of the displayed year. The Leave Ledger also displays a record of the “Days
        removed in correction” and “Inactive Leave Entries”. A link to the <emphasis
            role="underline">Current Leave Period</emphasis> at the top right side of the page takes
        returns to your leave calendars. </para>
    <para>The <emphasis role="underline">Leave Reques</emphasis>t link from the leave calendar
        displays planned leave blocks that have been placed on future leave calendars and can be
        submitted for approval. This page also contains Leave Request Pending Approval, Approved
        Leave Requests and Disapproved Leave Requests. Past and future year leave requests and
        approvals accruals can be accessed by using the scrolling buttons shown on each side of the
        displayed year. A link to the <emphasis role="underline">Current Leave Period</emphasis> at
        the top right side of the page takes returns to your leave calendars. </para>
    <section>
        <title>Adding/Editing/Deleting Leave Blocks to a Leave Calendar</title>
        <para>An employee who accrues leave hours such as paid time-off (PTO), vacation (VAC) or
            sick hours (SCK) will enter those hours either on their current timesheet if non-exempt
            or on their current leave calendar if exempt employee. <emphasis role="underline"
                >Adding, editing and deleting leave blocks to Leave Calendar works the same adding
                time to the Time Detail</emphasis>. </para>
        <para>Future leave hours can be added by scrolling forward to desired leave calendar period
            and adding a leave block. When adding a leave block, the request for leave can
            immediately be submitted for approval by checking “S ubmit leave request for approval”
            or the leave block can be added to the calendar as planned leave and later submitted for
            approval from the <emphasis role="underline">Leave Request</emphasis> page. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Viewing a Leave Summary</title>
        <para>Below the calendar is a section showing the leave summary. </para>
        <para>Accrual Category totals... </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Prior Year Carryover is the final accrued leave balance from the leave plan’s previous year.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>YTD (year to date) Earned is the total accruals along with any leave adjustments that have occurred since
                    the beginning of the Leave Plan’s start date to the first date of the leave calendar being displayed (i.e.
                    above example shows accruals up to March 17th).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>YTD Usage is the total usage since the beginning of the Leave Plan’s start date to the last date of the
                    leave calendar being displayed (i.e. above example totals include March 30th).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Accrued Balance is sum of the Prior Year Carryover and YTD Earned minus YTD Usage and future leave
                    usage</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Available Balance is the Usage Limit minus the YTD Usage.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Usage Limit is the accrual category’s rule applicable for the displayed leave calendar. When new usage
                    leave blocks are added to the calendar, the total YTD usage cannot exceed the Usage Limit if there is
                    one.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Future/Planned Usage is the total usage leave blocks that have been added to future leave calendars.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>YTD FMLA Usage is the total usage of leave blocks with an FMLA flagged earned code that exists on the
                    current and previous leave calendars.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The leave summary on leave calendars for the previous leave plan year will show the leave plan year’s totals. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Leave Requests</title>
        <para>Leave blocks are added to future leave calendars, they can be added to the leave
            calendar as a leave block with status of “planned” . To submit “planned” leave, click on
            the <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">Leave Request</emphasis></emphasis>
            link on the left under the document header. The Leave Request page has 4 different
            sections that leave blocks by leave block statuses: planned leave, requested leave that
            is pending approval, approved leave requests, and disapproved leave requests. </para>
        <para>The Planned Leave section displays leave blocks that can be submitted for approval.
            From the planned leave section, leave can be requested. Leave can also be requested when
            adding leave blocks or editing a leave block on a future leave calendar by checking
            “Submit leave request for approval” on the add Leave Block dialog box. Leave requests
            are routed for approval to the requested leave block’s assignment’s Work Area Approver.
            A leave block that has been submitted for approval will appear in the Leave Request
            Pending Approval section of the Leave Request page. Once the leave requested is
            approved, the leave block will appear on the Leave Request page as an Approved Leave
            Requests and the leave block will appear on the leave calendars as approved. If leave
            block will appear is disapproved the requested leave block will be removed from the
            leave calendar and will appear in the last section of the Leave Request page,
            Disapproved Leave Requests , with the approver’s reason . Approvers can also defer
            requested leave with a reason for deferring. Deferred leave blocks will return to status
            of “p lanned ” and the reason appears in the description on the Leave Request page. </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
