<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter xml:id="basic-setup" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
	<title>Basic Setup</title>
	<section>
		<title>Set up Calendars for leave and pay with leave entries</title>
		<section>
			<title>Calendar</title>
			<para>
				The system supports multiple pay cycles that are definable by
				start date
				/ time and end date / time.
				This allows for institutions to
				define multiple pay calendars such as
				monthly, semi-monthly,
				biweekly,
				or weekly. For example, an
				institution may define a pay
				period
				beginning at Noon on a Thursday
				which runs 2 weeks to 11:59:59
				am the
				following Thursday.
			</para>
			<para>
				The leave management module must allow for institutions to
				define
				calendars for which employees will report their leave. These
				calendars may or may not correspond to payroll calendars.
				For
				example,
				institutions may choose to define leave reporting calendars
				to be from
				the 15th of the month to the 15th of the following month
				while the
				payroll calendar may be from the 1st to the end of the
				month for the
				same employee.
			</para>
			<para>
				The system can define calendars for Pay and Leave. These
				Calendars will
				be furthered defined by the Calendar Entries
				maintenance document
				with the reporting periods and also associated
				with employees on the
				Principal HR Attributes Maintenance Document.
			</para>
			<table frame="none">
				<title>Calendar fields : </title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
					<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Field</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Calendar Name</entry>
							<entry>Text field used to defined the calendar entry for Pay or
								Leave reporting periods.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Calendar Descriptions</entry>
							<entry>Text field used to describe the calendar.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Calendar Types</entry>
							<entry>Indicate calendar is to be used for Pay or Leave reporting
								periods.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>FLSA Begin Day</entry>
							<entry>This value determines the FLSA period for overtime
								calculations.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>FLSA Begin Time</entry>
							<entry>Time of day when FLSA period begins.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Calendar Entries</title>
			<para>The system can define calendars for Pay, Leave, or Both. The
				Calendar Entry maintenance page defines the pay period (timesheet)
				and/or leave reporting period.  </para>
			<para>Entries must be created for a time period before a timesheet
				and/or leave calendar can be created. </para>
			<table frame="none">
				<title>Calendar Entries fields : </title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
					<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Field</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Calendar Name</entry>
							<entry>Calendar to be associated with Calendar Entries.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Begin Period Date/Time</entry>
							<entry>Date period starts. This drives what calendar days show on
								the timesheet and/or leaving calendar.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>End Period Date/Time</entry>
							<entry>Date period ends. This drives what calendars days show on
								the timesheetand/or leaving calendar.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Batch Initiate Date/Time</entry>
							<entry>Date batch should run to create timesheets and/or leaving
								calendars for the reporting period.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Batch End Pay Period Date/Time</entry>
							<entry>For Pay Calendar, date batch job should run to end all
								timeblocks for this pay period.
								This inserts clock outs at the end of the pay period, and clock ins
								at the beginning of the subsequent pay period.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Batch Employee Approval Date/Time</entry>
							<entry>Date batch job should run to route timesheets and/or leave calendars from the employee to the approver.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Batch Supervisor Approval Date/Time</entry>
							<entry>Date batch job should run to route timesheets and/or leave calendars from the approver to final status.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Earn Codes with Earn Code Security</title>
		<section>
			<title>Earn Code</title>
			<para>The Earn Code maintenance page is used to define codes to
				categorize employee’s hours/earnings and time off.
				For each earn
				code, you can define how the employees records - in/out
				time, hours,
				days or flat dollar amount.
				These codes may or may not be attached to
				an accrual category for
				tracking time against available balances or
				simple reporting..
				Most earn code attributes are defined in the
				payroll system,
				but there are a few codes which need to be modified
				on the timesheet
				prior to the data being extracted to payroll.
				An
				inflation factor and inflate minimum hours value are definable on
				the earn code document.
				These actions occur on the recorded hours in
				the timesheet, therefore
				would NOT need to be done in the payroll
				system.
				Additionally there are numerous flags on the earn code to
				limit availability and
				determine eligibility for accrual and
				scheduling leave.
			</para>
			<table frame="none">
				<title>Earn code fields : </title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
					<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Field</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Effective Date</entry>
							<entry>The Effective date for which the earn code will be
								effective. This date needs to be on/prior to the date the rule
								to takes effect.
								When editing, it will determine the date the new
								values go into
								effect.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Earn Code</entry>
							<entry>Alpha/Numeric code used to identify the earnings code.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Description</entry>
							<entry>Long description of earnings classification.</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
							<entry>Employees with the indicated Leave Plan may have access to
								this Earn Code on their Leave Calendar and Time Sheet
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Accrual Category</entry>
							<entry>If a category is entered the usage is validated against
								the employee’s balances.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Accrual Balance Action</entry>
							<entry>Supports validating against the Accrual Category
								associated with the Earn Code and instruct if it adjusts the
								balance of that category
								Usage should validate against the
								available balance subtract from the
								total
								Adjustment would work
								without validation and add/subtract the entry
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Fractional time allowed</entry>
							<entry>Define fractional unit of time used for reporting leave.
								Indicate number of decimals.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Rounding Option</entry>
							<entry>Used when calculating leave accruals and reporting.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Roll up to Earn Code</entry>
							<entry>This field allows earn codes to be associated with another
								for payroll extract.
								Ex: You could associate all the Sick codes
								with the regular sick
								earn code and not extract the detail
								into
								your payroll system (Sick family leave, sick injury, etc could
								all be extracted a
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Record Method</entry>
							<entry>Determines the value that will be entered for the earn
								code
								Time: earn code requires in/out times.
								Hours: earn code will
								require a hours amount
								Days: earn code will require a days amount
								Amount: earn code will require a dollar amount
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Overtime Earn Code</entry>
							<entry>Checked box indicates this may be used for overtime earn
								code. Codes with this checkbox are not available for entry on
								the timesheet.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Inflate Min Hours</entry>
							<entry>Hours incurred will be inflated to this minimum hours
								value. Ex: Call Back Time rules specify the employee earns a
								minimum number of hours, regardless of the time worked. Set an
								inflate minimum hours on the earn code and the employee will see
								the number of hours correctly on the timesheet, instead of
								assuming it will be inflated later.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Inflate Factor</entry>
							<entry>The hours incurred will be multiplied by this factor. Ex:
								Compensatory Time Earned (in lieu of overtime) is earned at
								a
								factor of 1.5. When the employee earns comp time, this setting
								will inflate the hours by a factor of 1.5 and all hours
								shown on
								the timesheet will be the inflated value. The employee will
								know
								the exact number of hours earned.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Eligible for Accrual</entry>
							<entry>Flag indicating this type of leave is eligible for
								accrual. This applies to all accrual categories the employee is
								eligible for.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Affect Pay</entry>
							<entry>Flag indicating use of this leave code will affect the
								employee's pay and can be used by schools who are extracting
								data to their payroll system. When leave code is used
								notification is sent to approver and department admin.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Allow Scheduled Leave</entry>
							<entry>Allow scheduling of leave on calendar (i.e. weather
								related leave).
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>FMLA</entry>
							<entry>FLMA Leave Code indicator. If Principal Calendar is
								flagged for FMLA,
								employee will have option to select this Leave
								Code.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Workman’s Comp</entry>
							<entry>Workman's Comp Leave Code indicator. If Principal Calendar
								is flagged for Workman’s Comp,
								employee will have option to
								select this Leave Code.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Default Amount of Time</entry>
							<entry>When a user selects leave code the specified amount of
								time will appear in
								the amount of leave taken. User can change
								the hours as needed once
								populated.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Allow Negative Accrual Balance</entry>
							<entry>Allows usage to take the balance of the Accrual Category
								into the negative.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Active</entry>
							<entry>Status of the category, checked indicates Active,
								unchecked indicates Inactive.
								If the rule is being eliminated,
								insert a new effective dated row
								and uncheck the active box.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
			<note>
				<para>
					Earn Codes must have an Earn Code Security entry to appear on
					the
					calendars. If an Earn Code does not have an Earn Code Security
					entry it will not be displayed by default.
				</para>
			</note>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Earn Code Security</title>
			<para>The Earn Code Security maintenance page is used to define which
				roles (employee, approver) see specific earn codes on the timesheet
				and/or Leave Calendar . This is definable at the department, salary
				group or location value. These fields are accept wild cards (%).
			</para>
			<para>Formerly called Department Earn Code in Timekeeping.
			</para>
			<table frame="none">
				<title>Earn Code Security fields : </title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
					<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Field</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>Effective Date</entry>
							<entry>The Effective date for which the department code rule will
								be effective. This date needs to be on/prior to the date the
								rule to takes effect.
								When editing, it will determine the date
								the new values go into
								effect.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Department</entry>
							<entry>If a department is defined, only entries associated with a
								job record in this department will be subject.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Salary Group</entry>
							<entry>If a salary group is defined, only entries associated with
								a job rcd in this salary group will be subject.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Earn Code</entry>
							<entry>This is the code to define values for earn/leave code.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Earn Code Type</entry>
							<entry>Determines if Earn Code should be displayed on Timesheet,
								Leave Calendar, or Both.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Location</entry>
							<entry>If a location is defined, only entries associated with a
								job rcd in this location will be subject.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Employee/Approver</entry>
							<entry>The role checked can select the specified code on the
								time/leave entry box.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>Active</entry>
							<entry>Status of the department code rule, checked indicates
								Active, unchecked indicates Inactive.
								If the rule is being
								eliminated, insert a new effective dated row
								and uncheck the
								active box.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Earn Code Groups</title>
		<para>
			The Earn Code Group maintenance page is used to define groupings
			of earn
			codes.
			In timekeeping, these groups are also used to define the
			summary
			sections on the timesheet and in the overtime rule setup page.
		</para>
		<para>
			Earn Code Groups can also be used to alert the user with a
			warning
			or
			additional information needed when using certain earn codes
			on their
			timesheet or leave calendar.
		</para>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>Earn Code Groups fields : </title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>The Effective date for which the department code rule will
							be effective. This date needs to be on/prior to the date the
							rule
							to takes effect.
							When editing, it will determine the date
							the new
							values go into
							effect.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Earn Group</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to identify the group.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text which describes the purpose of this grouping of earn
							codes.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Show on Summary</entry>
						<entry>Text which describes the purpose of this grouping of earn
							codes.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Status of the earn group, checked indicates Active,
							unchecked indicates Inactive. If the earn group is being
							eliminated, insert a new effective dated row and uncheck the
							active box.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>In the Earn Group Definitions section, add the earn codes
							to be included in this group. The description is pulled in when
							the code is added.
						</entry>
					</row>

				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>
</chapter>