<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="lm-admin" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Leave Management Administrative Tools</title>
    <section>
        <title>Balance Transfer</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/balancetransfermaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Balance Transfer Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Balance Transfer Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>
            Department, Location, and System Administrators have access to create and view Balance Transfer maintenance documents.  Admins can access to this 
            document is used to perform balance transfer transactions that are not triggered by the Accrual Category’s Max Balance limit and transfer action.  
            A new balance transfer record will create the leave blocks on the employee’s leave calendar that reflect the balance transfer amounts on the records 
            effective date.  On the approval type a note regarding the transaction will appears with the employee’s record.  
        </para>
        <table frame="none">
            <title>Balance Transfer fields :</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>Date the balance transfer will go into effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier of the employee.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Transfer From Accrual Category</entry>
                        <entry>The Accrual Category to transfer the amount from.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Transfer Amount</entry>
                        <entry>The amount to transfer.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Forfeited Amount</entry>
                        <entry>The computed amount that will be forfeited.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Transfer To Accrual Category</entry>
                        <entry>The Accrual Category to transfer the amount to.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Amount Transferred</entry>
                        <entry>The final amount transferred.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
	<section>
		<title>Employee Override</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/employeeoverridemaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Employee Override Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Employee Override Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
		<para>
			The system will allow for the ability to override the Accrual Category limits, such as usage, carryover, transfer or payout, for an individual 
			employee.  The system will check to see if the employee has an exception every time the logic is executed for
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        Max Balance – The system will use the indicated override value as the Accrual Category’s max balance.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
                        Max Transfer/Payout Amount – When a balance transfer transaction is preformed the limit for the maximum amount available to transfer or 
                        payout will be the indicated override value.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
                    <para>
                        Max Usage – On the employee’s leave calendar, when adding usage leave blocks the override value will be used to verify that the limit 
                        has not been exceeded.  On the leave calendar summary grid, the override value will appear in the max usage column for the Accrual 
                        Category.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
                    <para>
                        Max Annual Carryover – Annually, the max carryover is processed with approving the final leave calendar for the year.  The override 
                        value will be used when processing the annual carry over leave block.
                    </para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
            <note>
		        <para>
                    No limit is needed for any of the override types.  For example, if the override type of Max Usage and the Override Value is blank, the 
                    system will not apply a usage limit for this employee’s accrual category that typically has a usage limit.  
		        </para>
            </note>
		</para>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>Employee Override fields :</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the override will go into effect.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Principal ID</entry>
						<entry>Identifier of the employee.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
						<entry>Leave Plan associated with the Principal ID and Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to identify the Accrual Category the override will be applied to.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Type of Override</entry>
						<entry>Accrual Category limit that should be used for the Employee.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Override Value</entry>
						<entry>The new limit value to be used for the Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the reason for the override.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Active</entry>
						<entry>Status of the Override.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<note>
			<para>
				Access will be restricted to System Admins.
			</para>
		</note>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Leave Adjustment</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/leaveadjustmentmaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Leave Adjustment Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Leave Adjustment Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
		<para>
			Ability to modify a employee’s earn code accrual balance.  Restricted to System Admins or Department Admins with options to either create new or 
			view existing donation records.  On submit, a leave block will be generated and displayed on their leave calendar.
		</para>
        <para>
            An employee new to the system may have existing leave time from previous service.  To apply those hours to the employee’s new leave plan and accrual 
            categories, Leave Adjustment document for each accrual category can be create to adjust the employee’s balances to reflect the existing hours.    
        </para>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>Leave Adjustment fields :</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the adjustment will go into effect.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Principal ID</entry>
						<entry>Identifier of the employee.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Leave Plan</entry>
						<entry>Leave Plan associated with the Principal ID and Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to identify the Accrual Category the adjustment will be.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>Earn Code associated with the Accrual Category and leave adjustment.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Adjustment Amount</entry>
						<entry>The value of the leave adjustment, positive or negative.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the reason for the adjustment.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<note>
			<para>
				An employee will not have ability to modify their own leave balances.
			</para>
		</note>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Leave Donation</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/leavedonationmaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Leave Donation Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Leave Donation Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
		<para>
			Employee's may donate leave to another employee.  The donation transaction is done by the system admin with option to create new or view existing 
			donation records.  On submit leave blocks are generated for both recipient and donor that will display on their leave calendar. Leave donation may 
			or may not be prorated according to the donor and recipient's salary.  Amount Donated and Amount Received must be manually entered and is what will 
			be removed/added from the designated Accrual Categories.
		</para>
		<table frame="none">
			<title>Leave Donation fields :</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
				<colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Field</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Effective Date</entry>
						<entry>Date the Donation transaction will go into effect.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Donor's Principal ID</entry>
						<entry>Identifier of the employee donating leave.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Donation Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Accrual Category associated with the donated Leave.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Donation Earn Code</entry>
						<entry>A leave block indicating the amount donated will be recorded with this earn code.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Amount Donated</entry>
						<entry>The amount of accrued leave to be donated. Subtracted from the Donated Leave Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Recipient's Principal ID</entry>
						<entry>Identifier of the employee receiving the donated leave.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Recipient's Accrual Category</entry>
						<entry>Accrual Category the donated Leave will be accrued to.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Recipient's Earn Code </entry>
						<entry>The donation accrual leave block will be recorded with this earn code.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Amount Received</entry>
						<entry>The amount of accrued leave to be received. Added to the Recipient's Leave Accrual Category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>Text field used to describe the reason for the Leave Donation.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>		
	</section>
	<section>
        <title>Leave Payout</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../images/lm/leavepayoutmaint.jpg" format="JPG" scale="40"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Leave Payout Maintenance Document</phrase>
            </textobject>
            <caption>The Leave Payout Maintenance Document</caption>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>
            Payout maintenance document can be used to payout earned accruals. Department, Location, and System Administrators can use this document to preform 
            payout transactions that are not triggered by the Accrual Category’s Max Balance limit and the payout action.  Example uses of this document maybe 
            need to process a payout of earned accrual at time of termination/retirement.  After the document is submitted and approved, using the effective 
            leave blocks that reflect the payout transaction will be created for the appropriate Accrual Category.  The payout earn code will need to be fed to 
            payroll for the payout to be processed.  
        </para>
        <table frame="none">
            <title>Leave Payout fields :</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*" />
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.00*" />
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>Identifier of the employee.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Earn Code</entry>
                        <entry>Earn code that is associated with the Payout Amount and fed to Payroll.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>Date the leave payout will go into effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Payout From Accrual Category</entry>
                        <entry>Accrual Category to pay leave out of.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Payout Amount</entry>
                        <entry>The amount of leave to pay out.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Forfeited Amount</entry>
                        <entry>Computed amount of accrued leave that will be forfeited.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>        
    </section>
</chapter>