<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="tk-config" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>TimeKeeping Configuration</title>
    <para>This chapter discusses all rules and configurations for Timekeeping module of KPME. All
        rules and configurations can be accessed through maintenance documents listed under
        <emphasis role="bold">Time Keeping</emphasis> section on the maintenance tab. </para>
    <section>
        <title>Clock Location Rule</title>
        <para>This feature enables administrates to define approved IP addresses for clock entry.
            Clock location rules can be set system wide, or as granular as a specific employee job
            record. The most specific rule for that assignment will be enforced. </para>
        <important>
            <para>A clock location rule will not restrict the clock action from an unapproved IP but
                will add a note to the timesheet that the clock action was from an "unapproved
                location".</para>
        </important>
        <para>Regardless of a rule, the IP address is captured on every clock action and can be seen
            in the Clock Log Inquiry page.</para>
        <para> Table below shows fields used to record and maintain a clock location rule along with
            their description.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Clock Location Rule Document Fields</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>fields</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                    </row>

                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>The Effective date for which the IP address validation will be
                            effective. This date needs to be on/prior to the date the rule to takes
                            effect. When editing, it will determine the date the new values go into
                            effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Department</entry>
                        <entry>If a department is defined, only entries associated with a job in
                            that department will be subject to IP address validation. Wild card of
                            (%) is acceptable as input for this field. Validates against the
                            department table.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Work Area</entry>
                        <entry>If a work area is defined, only entries associated with a job in this
                            work area will be subject to IP address validation. Wild card of (%) is
                            acceptable input. Validates against the work area table.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>If a principal id is defined, only this specific employee will be
                            subject to IP address validation. Wild card of (%) is acceptable as
                            input for this field.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Job Number</entry>
                        <entry>If a job number is defined, only this specific employees job will be
                            subject to IP address validation. Wild card of (%) is acceptable as
                            input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>IP Address</entry>
                        <entry>The IP Address to be used for validation. A wild card can be placed
                            at the end of a partial IP address to represent a range of IP addresses.
                            To grant exceptions to rules in effect, wild card the IP address
                            field.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Active</entry>
                        <entry>Status of the IP validation rule, checked indicates Active, unchecked
                            indicates Inactive.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <tip>
            <para> To eliminate a clock location rule, insert a new effective dated row and uncheck
                the active box. </para>
        </tip>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Daily Overtime Rule</title>
        <para> The Daily Overtime Rule is used to define the parameters by which daily overtime is
            calculated. This calculation runs prior to the weekly overtime calculation and can be
            limited to specific populations by paytype, location, dept, and work area. All of these
            parameters can be replaced by a wild card value (%) allowing the user to designate a
            rule at different levels. </para>
        <para> The table below lists all fields on the Daily Overtime Rule Document along with their
            descriptions. </para>
        <table>
            <title>Daily Overtime Rule Document fields</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>fields</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>Effective date for which the daily overtime rule will be effective.
                            This date needs to be on/prior to the date the rule to takes effect.
                            When editing, it will determine the date the new values go into
                            effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Location</entry>
                        <entry>If a location is defined, only entries associated with a job in this
                            location will be subject to the defined rule. Validates against the
                            location table.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Department</entry>
                        <entry>If a department is defined, only entries associated with a job in
                            this department will be subject to the defined rule. Validates against
                            the department table.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Work Area</entry>
                        <entry>If a work area is defined, only entries associated with a job that
                            has this work area will be subject. Validates against the work area
                            table.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Max Gap Minutes</entry>
                        <entry>Used to identify a maximum gap of time in minutes that is allowed
                            before daily overtime is considered invalid. For example, a rule that
                            states daily overtime is given for working over 8 hours with a max gap
                            of 30 minutes implies that employee must work a total of 8 hours in the
                            day and have a gap of no more than 30 minutes in the reporting of those
                            hours to be eligible.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Shift Hours</entry>
                        <entry>The number of hours which, if exceeded, result in daily
                            overtime.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Convert to Earn Code</entry>
                        <entry>The earn code which hours will be converted to as overtime. Only earn
                            codes that are designated as an Overtime Earn Code can be used (see Earn
                            Code Maintenance Document).</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Convert from Earn Group</entry>
                        <entry>The earn group defined (using the Earn Group maint doc) which
                            contains the list of earn codes that are summed to the daily max hours
                            to be converted to overtime.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Active</entry>
                        <entry>Status of the rule, checked indicates Active, unchecked indicates
                            Inactive. If the rule is being eliminated, insert a new effective dated
                            row and uncheck the active box.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Weekly Overtime Rule</title>
        <para> The Weekly Ovetime Rule defines the steps necessary to calculate weekly overtime.
            This maintenance document page allows the user to establish which earn codes count
            towards the calculation of overtime hours, what overtime earn code to use and where the
            overtime hours should be applied. This maintenance document is different because there
            is only one Weekly Overtime rule in effect at a time. </para>
        <note>
            <para>There is no create new link, the link directs straight to the page to add steps to
                or edit the existing steps.</para>
        </note>
        <table>
            <title>Weekly Overtime Rule Document fields</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>field</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>Effective date for which the Weekly Overtime Rule will be effective.
                            This date needs to be on or prior to the date the rule to take effect.
                            When editing, it will determine the date the new values go into
                            effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Max Hours Earn Group</entry>
                        <entry>The earn group defined (using the Earn Group maintenance document) to
                            represent the codes which count towards the calculation of
                            overtime.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Convert from Earn Group</entry>
                        <entry>The earn group defined to represent the earn codes to be converted to
                            overtime. If there is only one step in overtime calulcation, this will
                            be the same earn group as max hours earn group. If there are multiple
                            steps, this will be an earn group which is a subset of the max hours
                            earn group.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Convert to Earn Code</entry>
                        <entry>The default earn code which other earnings will be converted to (ex:
                            OVT). Only earn codes that are designated as an Overtime Earn Code can
                            be used (see Earn Code Maintenance Document). This earn code is used for
                            overtime hours unless the Work Area for the Assignment has a designated
                            Default Overtime Earn Code (see Work Area Maintenance Document).</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Step</entry>
                        <entry>This enables the definition of multiple steps in the hours conversion
                            for overtime.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Max Hours</entry>
                        <entry>Define the maximum hours in an FLSA period for overtime calculation
                            (ex: 40)</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title> Department Lunch Deduction Rule </title>
        <para>The Department Lunch Deduction rule is used to define automatic lunch deductions. This
            rule only applies to clock entry employees and rules can be set system wide, or as
            granular as on a specific employee job record. The most specific rule for a given
            assignment will be enforced. Employees subject to the automatic lunch time deduction
            will not see the <emphasis role="bold">lunch in/out</emphasis> buttons (even if that
            system setting is enabled).</para>
        <table>
            <title>Department Lunch Deduction Rule Document fields</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>field</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>The Effective date for which the automatic lunch deduction rule will
                            be effective. This date needs to be on/prior to the date the rule to
                            take effect. When editing, it will determine the date the new values go
                            into effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Department</entry>
                        <entry>If a department is defined, only entries associated with a job in
                            this department will be subject to the automatic lunch deduction. Wild
                            card of (%) is acceptable as input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Work Area</entry>
                        <entry>If a work area is defined, only entries associated with a job in this
                            work area will be subject to the automatic lunch deduction. Wild card of
                            (%) is acceptable as input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>If a principal id is defined, only this specific employee will be
                            subject to the automatic lunch deduction. Wild card of (%) is acceptable
                            as input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Job Number</entry>
                        <entry>If job number is defined, only this specific employees job will be
                            subject to the automatic lunch deduction. Wild card of (%) is acceptable
                            as input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Lunch Deduction Minutes</entry>
                        <entry>The amount of minutes to be deducted as a lunch.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Shift Hours</entry>
                        <entry>The number of hours which must be met in order for the deduction to
                            occur.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Active</entry>
                        <entry>Status of the automatic lunch deduction rule, checked indicates
                            Active, unchecked indicates Inactive.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>User Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>User which set up the lunch rule.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <tip>
            <para>To elimiante an existing rule, insert a new effective dated row and uncheck the
                active box.</para>
        </tip>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Grace Period Rule</title>
        <para>The Grace Period Rule is an optional rule that results in the system rounding clock
            in/outs times based on the chosen factor. This rule rounds up and down based on the
            clock action time. The benefit of having a graec period rule is that it eliminates small
            fractions of time and makes calculations less complicated for those employees trying to
            reach standard hours for the week. It also alleviates the rush to clock in or out right
            on the hour. </para>
        <table>
            <title>Grace period rule</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Rounded Time</entry>
                        <entry>Actual Clock in time</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:00</entry>
                        <entry>:57, :58, :59, <emphasis role="bold">:00</emphasis>, :01, :02</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:06</entry>
                        <entry>:03, :04, :05, <emphasis role="bold">:06</emphasis>, :07, :08</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:12</entry>
                        <entry>:09, :10, :11, <emphasis role="bold">:12</emphasis>, :13, :14</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:18</entry>
                        <entry>:15, :16, :17, <emphasis role="bold">:18</emphasis>, :19, :20</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:24</entry>
                        <entry>:21, :22, :23, <emphasis role="bold">:24</emphasis>, :25, :26</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:30</entry>
                        <entry>:27, :28, :29, <emphasis role="bold">:30</emphasis>, :31, :32</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:36</entry>
                        <entry>:33, :34, :35, <emphasis role="bold">:36</emphasis>, :37, :38</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:42</entry>
                        <entry>:39, :40, :41, <emphasis role="bold">:42</emphasis>, :43, :44</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:48</entry>
                        <entry>:45, :46, :47, <emphasis role="bold">:48</emphasis>, :49, :50</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>:54</entry>
                        <entry>:51, :52, :53, <emphasis role="bold">:54</emphasis>, :55, :56</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Shift Differential Rule</title>
        <para>The Shift Differential Rule defines rules for assigning shift differentials. This rule
            applies shift automatically to earn codes when clock times are specified. If an earn
            code is entered with an hours amount (ex: Sick), the rule would not assign shift. Rules
            can be set system wide, or on specific populations (most specific rule for that
            assignment will be enforced). The rule will add a specified earn code to the eligible
            shift hours. Different earn codes are needed to result in different shift amounts (eg
            each earn code attached to a shift rule has its own associated rate for payment in
            Payroll). The shift differential rule only assigns the additional earnings codes to
            shift hours within the specified shift time period. Any hours outside of the shift
            period will not be assigned shift.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Shift Differential Rule</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>field</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>The effective date which the shift differential rule will be
                            effective. This date needs to be on or prior to the date the rule to
                            take effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Location</entry>
                        <entry>If a location is defined, only entries associated with a job in this
                            location will be subject to the shift rule. Wild card of (%) is
                            acceptable as input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Salary Group</entry>
                        <entry>If a salary group is defined, only entries associated with a job in
                            this salary group will be subject to the shift rule. Wild card of (%) is
                            acceptable as input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Pay Grade</entry>
                        <entry>If a pay grade is defined, onlye entries associated with a job in
                            this pay grade will be subject to the shift rule. Wild card of (%) is an
                            acceptable input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Earn Code</entry>
                        <entry>The earn code that will be applied to the eligible shift </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>From Earn Group</entry>
                        <entry>The earn group defined to represent the earn codes to be converted to
                            <emphasis role="italic">Shif Differential Earn
                                Code</emphasis>.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Begin Time</entry>
                        <entry>The beginning time of the eligible shift.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>End Time</entry>
                        <entry>The end time of the eligible shift. This could be on the following
                            day if the eligible shift is overnight.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Minimum Hours</entry>
                        <entry>The minimum number of hours a shift must be in order to qualify for
                            shift differential. A zero in this field would mean that there is no
                            minimum shift requirement.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Sun-Sat checkboxes</entry>
                        <entry>Check which days are eligible for shift differential.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Maximum Gap Minutes</entry>
                        <entry>The maximum number of minutes which can separate time blocks, and
                            still qualify as an eligible shift.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>User Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>User that set up the shift rule.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Active</entry>
                        <entry>Status of the shift differential rule.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Calendar Group</entry>
                        <entry>Pay Calendar record that defines the FLSA period.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>System Lunch Rule</title>
        <para>System lunch rule is a system level setting which determines if the “Take Lunch” and
            “Return from Lunch” buttons display for clock entry employees. If the employee is
            subject to a lunch deduction rule, no lunch buttons will be displayed.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Fields on System Lunch Rule Document</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>field</entry>
                        <entry>description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>Effective date for which the system lunch rule will be effective.
                            This date needs to be on or prior to the date of the rule to take
                            effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Show Lunch Button</entry>
                        <entry>When checked, Lunch buttons will be presented</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Active</entry>
                        <entry>Status of the rule, checked indicates Active, unchecked indicates
                            Inactive.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <tip>
            <para>To eliminate a system lunch rule, insert a new effective dated row and uncheck the
                active checkbox.</para>
        </tip>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Time Collection Rule</title>
        <para>The Time Collection Rule maintenance page is used to define how employees record time,
            via clock entry or manual entry. This rule can be defined at various levels including at
            a system level. The timesheet shows the clock tab for entry if the most specific rule
            for that assignment is marked as a clock user.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Time Collection Rule Document Fields</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Field</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Effective Date</entry>
                        <entry>The Effective date for which the time collection rule will be
                            effective. This date needs to be on or prior to the date of the rule to
                            take effect.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Department</entry>
                        <entry>Department the time collection rule is associated with. A wild card
                            (%) can be provided indicating the rule is in effect for all
                            departments.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Work Area</entry>
                        <entry>Work area the time collection rule is associated with. A wild card
                            (%) can be provided indicating the rule is in effect for all work
                            areas.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Pay Type</entry>
                        <entry/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Clock User</entry>
                        <entry>If this box is checked, clock entry will be required for recording
                            time based on the department and work area values provided
                            above.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Hour Distribution</entry>
                        <entry>Used to allow employees to clock in and out of a single assignment
                            and then distribute hours at the end of the day to multiple
                            assignments.Hours distribution is only available for time blocks
                            createdby the clock.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>User Principal ID</entry>
                        <entry>Auto populated by the Principal ID of user who created the
                            rule.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Active</entry>
                        <entry>Status of the Time Collection Rule, checked indicates Active,
                            unchecked indicates Inactive.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
</chapter>
