<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> 
<chapter xml:id="setup" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"  version="5.0">    
    <title>Setup</title>
    <para>
        This chapter is designed to provide simple step-by-step instructions on how to set up a KPME server intended for enterprise deployment with an
        existing Rice server.
    </para>
    <para>The steps to install and setup an embedded server with KPME are:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Determine your expected load and storage needs and consult the Suggested Server Hardware section for guidance. Install OS.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Install &amp; configure the database management system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Install &amp; configure required software</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Install and configure Tomcat.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Install and configure KPME.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Launch KPME.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <note>
        <para>
            Rather than install and setup as the root user on systems designed for production, you may want to create a non-privilieged user named something 
            like 'kpme' to use for this purpose.
        </para>
    </note>
    <section>
        <title>Suggested Server Hardware</title>
        <para>
            Note that hardware needs may vary depending on the amount of expected load, the operating system being used, and the number of applications that 
            are integrated with KPME. KPME is typically deployed as a client application connected to a separate Rice server, each with their own separate 
            database deployed on separate database server from either application.
        </para>
        <para>The recommended minimum requirements are as follows:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Two processor cores of a recent CPU architecture along with 2 GB of reserved RAM.  Minimum hardware and settings for the database should be 
                    based on vendor recommendations, but there should be high bandwidth with low latency between the web application and database as this is a 
                    database intensive application.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    At least 1 GB of heap space (-Xmx1g) and 256 MB of permanent generation space (-XX:MaxPermSize=256m) reserved for the application to start 
                    and run. For production use, at least 2 GB of heap and 512 MB of permanent generation space are recommended.
                </para>
                <note>
                    <para>
                        Other recommended settings are -server (to improve resource utilization for long-running tasks) and -XX:+UseConcMarkSweepGC (to improve 
                        garbage collection performance).
                    </para>
                </note>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>100 Mbit/s network card (gigabit preferred)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>200 MB of hard disk space (for Tomcat server and web application)</para>
                <note><para>Additional space needed if storing attachments.</para></note>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Installing and Configuring the Database Management System</title>
        <para>
            KPME was developed using two relational database management systems: <emphasis role="bold">MySQL</emphasis> and 
            <emphasis role="bold">Oracle</emphasis>. The typical production install involves running the KPME application separate from the database server, 
            however both can be run on the same machine for development purposes.
        </para>
        <para>KPME runs, and has been tested with the following versions:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Oracle</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Oracle Database 10g</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Oracle Database 11g</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Oracle Express Edition (XE)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Use the Oracle JDBC Driver to connect to these databases.</para>
                <para>
                    Ensure that the Oracle database you intend to use encodes character data in a UTF variant by default. For Oracle XE, this entails 
                    downloading the "Universal" flavor of the binary, which uses AL32UTF8.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>MySQL</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>MySQL 5.1.+</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Use the MySQL Connector/J (5.1.+) to connect to MySQL databases.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            You should be able to adapt KPME to other standard relational databases (e.g., Sybase, Microsoft SQL Server, DB2, etc.). However, this Installation 
            Guide does not provide information for running KPME with these products.
        </para>
        <section xml:id="database_software_locations">
            <title>Locations for Database Software</title>
            <para>Below are locations from which Oracle and MySQL could be downloaded at the time of release of Rice ${project.version}.</para>
            <table frame="none">
                <title>Locations for Database Software</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4.11*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Software</entry>
                            <entry>Download Location</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Oracle Standard and Enterprise Editions</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <link xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/database/enterprise-edition/downloads/index.html">http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/database/enterprise-edition/downloads/index.html</link>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Oracle Express Edition</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <link xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/database/express-edition/downloads/index.html">http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/database/express-edition/downloads/index.html</link>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Oracle JDBC DB Driver</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <link xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/database/features/jdbc/index-091264.html">http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/database/features/jdbc/index-091264.html</link>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>MySQL </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <link xlink:href="http://www.mysql.com/downloads/">http://www.mysql.com/downloads/</link>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>MySQL Connector/J JDBC Driver</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <link xlink:href="http://www.mysql.com/products/connector/j/">http://www.mysql.com/products/connector/j/</link>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>MySQL Database Preparation</title>
            <para>
                KPME supports both MySQL and Oracle databases. However, MySQL is easier to install than Oracle and uses less machine resources so many 
                developers prefer to use that when getting started with KPME.
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Installation</title>
                <para>
                    The installation steps for MySQL are going to be different for each platform.  Please download the latest version MySQL Server from the 
                    location listed in the <link linkend="database_software_locations">Locations for Database Software</link> section of this document and 
                    follow the installation instructions for your platform.
                </para>
                <note>
                    <para>
                        You may be required to create an account on the MySQL site in order to download the software.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Please be sure to follow the instructions for installing MySQL on your platform very carefully. If downloading for Mac OS X, 
                        <emphasis role="bold">be careful</emphasis> to download the appropriate version for your platform (32-bit vs. 64-bit and 10.6 vs 10.7)
                    </para>
                </note>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>
                    There are a few MySQL database configuration options that are required in order for KPME to work properly. These will need to be set in 
                    either your <emphasis role="bold">my.cnf</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">my.ini</emphasis> file. The location and names of these files 
                    will differ depending on which platform you are working on. For details on where these files can be found, see the following document:
                </para>
                <para>
                    <link xlink:href="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.1/en/option-files.html">http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.1/en/option-files.html</link>
                </para>
                <para>
                    Once you have located this file, please add the following options, paying special attention to the line that needs to be commented out:
                </para>
                <programlisting>[mysqld]
max_allowed_packet=20M
transaction-isolation=READ-COMMITTED
lower_case_table_names=1
max_connections=1000
innodb_locks_unsafe_for_binlog=1
...
# Be sure to comment this out if it's in the file!!!
#log-bin=mysql-bin</programlisting>
                <para>
                    Note that the <emphasis role="bold">[mysqld]</emphasis> section may already be in your <emphasis role="bold">my.cnf</emphasis> file.  If 
                    so, you can just add the options listed above underneath that section
                </para>
                <caution>
                    <para>
                        It is very important that you comment out <emphasis role="bold">log-bin</emphasis>.  Otherwise you will end up with some very bad 
                        problems later!
                    </para>
                </caution>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Verification</title>
                <para>
                    Before verifying your mysql installation you will need to ensure that MySQL is running. Some of the platform-specific packages will set 
                    this up automatically (or allow you to install yourself in the case of Mac OS X). If MySQL is not starting automatically you can start it 
                    using a command like the following example from Mac OS X:
                </para>
                <programlisting>sudo /usr/local/mysql/bin/mysqld_safe</programlisting>
                <para>This will start the MySQL server.</para>
                <para>To verify that you can actually connect to the server, execute the following at the command line:</para>
                <programlisting>mysql -u root -p</programlisting>
                <para>
                    This should bring you to a command line client interface for the MySQL server.  Type "show databases;" and press return. You should see 
                    output similar to the following.
                </para>
                <programlisting>Welcome to the MySQL monitor.  Commands end with ; or \g.
Your MySQL connection id is 1
Server version: 5.1.50-log MySQL Community Server (GPL)

Copyright (c) 2000, 2010, Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.
This software comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY. This is free software,
and you are welcome to modify and redistribute it under the GPL v2 license

Type 'help;' or '\h' for help. Type '\c' to clear the current input statement.

mysql> show databases;
+--------------------+
| Database           |
+--------------------+
| information_schema |
| mysql              |
| test               |
+--------------------+
3 rows in set (0.13 sec)

mysql></programlisting>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Install the JDBC Driver</title>
                <para>
                    KPME uses the MySQL Connector/J product as the native JDBC driver.  During installation, Maven will automatically download and install this
                    driver, so no additional action is necessary.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>    
        <section>
            <title>Oracle Database Preparation</title>
            <section>
                <title>Installation</title>
                <para>
                    The installation steps for Oracle are going to be different for each platform and version of Oracle. Please download from the location 
                    listed in the <link linkend="database_software_locations">Locations for Database Software</link> section of this document and follow the 
                    installation instructions for your platform.
                </para>
                <para>
                    To run the database completely on your local machine, we recommend installing Oracle Express (XE). Please refer to the 
                    <link linkend="database_software_locations">Locations for Database Software</link> section of this Installation Guide to find the download 
                    location for this software.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>
                    By default, OracleXE registers a web user interface on port 8080. This is the same port that the development version of KPME is 
                    preconfigured to use. To avoid a port conflict, you must change the port that the OracleXE web user interface uses with the Oracle XE admin 
                    webapp:
                    <figure>
                        <title>Oracle XE admin webapp</title>
                        <mediaobject>    
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="../images/oracle_xe_admin_webapp.png" width="5.75in"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </para>
                <para>
                    If you prefer, you can use the Oracle SQL tool described here to change the OracleXE web user interface port: 
                    <link xlink:href="http://daust.blogspot.com/2006/01/xe-changing-default-http-port.html">http://daust.blogspot.com/2006/01/xe-changing-default-http-port.html</link>
                </para>
                <para>
                    Please edit your hosts file with an entry to refer to your Oracle database.  When this Installation Guide refers to the Oracle database 
                    host server, it will be referred to in the examples as koracle.
                </para>
                <para>Now edit the hosts file and add this:</para>
                <programlisting>&lt;ip address of mysql server&gt; koracle</programlisting>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Verification</title>
                <para>
                    Before verifying your oracle installation you will need to ensure that Oracle is running. Some of the platform-specific packages will set 
                    this up automatically.  If Oracle is not starting automatically you can start it using a command like the following example from Ubuntu:
                </para>
                <programlisting>sudo /etc/init.d/oracle start</programlisting>
                <para>This will start the Oracle server.</para>
                <para>To verify that you can actually connect to the server, execute the following at the command line:</para>
                <programlisting>sqlplus</programlisting>
                <para>
                    This should bring you to a command line client interface for the Oracle server.
                </para>
                <programlisting>SQL*Plus: Release 10.2.0.1.0 - Production on Fri Nov 2 12:27:12 2012

Copyright (c) 1982, 2005, Oracle.  All rights reserved.


SQL></programlisting>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Install the JDBC Driver</title>
                <para>KPME uses the standard Oracle JDBC driver as the native JDBC driver.</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Please download this driver from the location specified in the 
                            <link linkend="database_software_locations">Locations for Database Software</link> section of this Guide.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            If you do not already have Maven 3 installed, install it now using the instructions in the <link linkend="maven">Maven</link> 
                            section.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Use the <link xlink:href="http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-install-plugin">maven-install-plugin</link> to copy ojdbc14.jar 
                            into your local maven repository.</para>
                        <programlisting>mvn install:install-file -DgroupId=com.oracle -DartifactId=ojdbc14 \
                         -Dversion=10.2.0.3.0 -Dpackaging=jar \
                         -Dfile=ojdbc14.jar</programlisting>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Suggested SQL Client Software</title>
            <para>
                To examine and test your database setup, SQL client software is useful. Any SQL client software that will connect to a MySQL or Oracle database 
                will work. Two tools used by the development team are the MySQL Workbench and Oracle SQL Developer.
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>MySQL Workbench</title>
                <para>
                    MySQL Workbench only works with MySQL and and can be installed to connect to any running MySQL server.  You can download and install it 
                    from the following URL:
                </para>
                <para>
	                <itemizedlist>
	                    <listitem>
	                        <para><link xlink:href="http://www.mysql.com/downloads/workbench/">http://www.mysql.com/downloads/workbench/</link></para>
	                    </listitem>
	                </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Oracle SQL Developer</title>
                <para>
                    Oracle SQL Developer is a Java-based program mainly used to connect to Oracle databases (but can connect to MySQL databases with a plugin).  
                    You can download and install it from the following URL:
                </para>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><link xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/developer-tools/sql-developer/overview/index.html">http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/developer-tools/sql-developer/overview/index.html</link></para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section> 
    <section>
        <title>Install and Configure Required Software</title>
        <section>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>KPME requires the following software to be setup and configured:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Sun Microsystems Java Development Kit (JDK 1.6.x)</para>
                        <warning>
                            <para>
                                You must use a JDK and not a Java runtime environment (JRE); the JDK you use must be version 1.6.x. Additionally, KPME has not 
                                been tested on JDKs other than Sun. So alternative implementations like OpenJDK should be used at your own risk.
                            </para>
                        </warning>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Maven 3</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="environment_variables">
            <title>Environment Variables</title>
            <para>First, some environment variables need to be configured.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Mac OS X</title>
                <para>
                    Environment variables in Mac OS X can be set in a number of ways, but here we will show how to modify or create the .profile files in 
                    your user home directory. On OS X your user home directory is typically located at /Users/&lt;username&gt;.
                </para>
                <para>An example .profile can be found below:</para>
                <programlisting>M2_HOME=/usr/local/maven
MAVEN_OPTS="-Xmx1024m -XX:MaxPermSize=768m"
JAVA_HOME=/System/Library/Frameworks/JavaVM.framework/Versions/1.6/Home
CATALINA_HOME=/usr/local/tomcat
MYSQL_HOME=/usr/local/mysql
    
PATH="$M2_HOME/bin:$CATALINA_HOME:$MYSQL_HOME/bin:$PATH"
export PATH M2_HOME MAVEN_OPTS JAVA_HOME CATALINA_HOME MYSQL_HOME</programlisting>
                <note><para>It is important to export your environment variables once they are defined as the file above does.</para></note>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Windows XP</title>
                <para>To get to the screen where you can define environment variables on Windows XP follow these steps:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click on the "Start" button in the bottom left-hand corner.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>On the resulting screen, right click on "My Computer".</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>In the context menu, click on "Properties".</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This will open up the "System Properties" dialog window.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click on the "Advanced" tab.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click on the "Environment Variables" button.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>You will see the screen where you can edit existing environment variables or define new ones.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <note>
                    <para>The windows command line console must be closed and reopened in order for environment variable changes to be effective.</para>
                </note>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Windows Vista and Windows 7</title>
                <para>To get to the screen where you can define environment variables on Windows Vista or Windows 7 follow these steps:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click on the "Start" button in the bottom left-hand corner.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>On the resulting screen, right click on "Computer".</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>In the context menu, click on "Properties".</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>This will open up the Control Panel "System" dialog.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click on the "Advanced system settings".</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>In the resulting window, click on the "Environment Variables..."
                            button.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>You will see the screen where you can edit existing environment variables or define new ones.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <note>
                    <para>The windows command line console must be closed and reopened in order for environment variable changes to be effective.</para>
                </note>
            </section>
        </section> 
        <section>
            <title>Java SDK</title>
            <section>
                <title>Installation</title>
                <para>
                    You should download and install the latest version of JDK 6. If you are on Windows, you can download it from the following URL: 
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html">http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/downloads/index.html</link>.
                </para>
                <para>
                    If you are on a Mac, then Java 6 should alredy be installed if you are up to date with the latest updates from Apple.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>
                    You will also want to set up your <emphasis role="bold">JAVA_HOME</emphasis> environment variable to point to the installation directory of 
                    your JDK. In both Windows and Mac environments, the <emphasis role="bold">java</emphasis> executable program should already be on your 
                    path. But if it is not, you will want to include <emphasis role="bold">JAVA_HOME/bin</emphasis> in your 
                    <emphasis role="bold">PATH</emphasis> environment variable.
                </para>
                <para>
                    If you do not know how to do this, see the <command linkend="environment_variables">Environment Variables</command> section above for your 
                    platform.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Verification</title>
                <para>
                    In order to verify that your JDK has been installed successfully, open a command prompt and type the following:
                </para>
                <programlisting>java -version</programlisting>
                <para>You should see output similar to the following:</para>
                <programlisting>java version "1.6.0_26"
Java(TM) SE Runtime Environment (build 1.6.0_26-b03-383-11A511)
Java HotSpot(TM) 64-Bit Server VM (build 20.1-b02-383, mixed mode)</programlisting>
                <para>
                    If you receive an error indicating that the "java" command could not be found, please ensure that the java command is on your machine's 
                    <emphasis role="bold">PATH</emphasis> environment variable.
                </para>
                <para>
                    To prevent potential out of memory errors when running KPME, you should set your <emphasis role="bold">JAVA_OPTS</emphasis> environment to 
                    a value like the following:
                </para>
                <programlisting>JAVA_OPTS="-Xmx1024m -XX:MaxPermSize=768m"</programlisting>
                <para>
                    If you do not know how to do this, see the <link linkend="environment_variables">Environment Variables</link> section above for your 
                    platform.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="maven">
            <title>Maven</title>
            <para>
                Maven is the primary build tool used by the Kuali Rice project. Maven is based on a project object model (POM) that defines various standards 
                and conventions surrounding the organization of a project. This faciliates a set of standard build goals and lifecycle phases (such as compile, 
                test, package, etc.).
            </para>
            <section>
                <title>Installation</title>
                <para>
                    To download version 3 of Maven, use the following link: 
                    <link xlink:href="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">http://maven.apache.org/download.html</link>
                </para>
                <para>Once you have downloaded the zip file, unzip it to a location of your choosing.</para>
            </section>    
            <section>
                <title>Configuration</title>
                <para>
                    You will want to set your <emphasis role="bold">M2_HOME</emphasis> environement variable to point to the location where you unzipped Maven.  
                    You will additionally want to include <emphasis role="bold">M2_HOME/bin</emphasis> in your <emphasis role="bold">PATH</emphasis> 
                    environment variable so that maven can be executed from the command line without having to specify the full path.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Finally, to prevent potential out of memory errors when compiling KPME with Maven, you should set your 
                    <emphasis role="bold">MAVEN_OPTS</emphasis> environment to a value like the following:
                </para>
                <programlisting>MAVEN_OPTS="-Xmx1024m -XX:MaxPermSize=768m"</programlisting>
                <para>
                    If you do not know how to do this, see the <link linkend="environment_variables">Environment Variables</link> section above for your 
                    platform.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Verification</title>
                <para>
                    In order to verify that Maven has been installed successfully and is available on the path, open a command prompt and type the following:
                </para>
                <programlisting>mvn -version</programlisting>
                <para>You should see output like the following:</para>
                <programlisting>Apache Maven 3.0.3 (r1075438; 2011-02-28 10:31:09-0700)
Maven home: /usr/local/maven
Java version: 1.6.0_26, vendor: Apple Inc.
Java home: /System/Library/Java/JavaVirtualMachines/1.6.0.jdk/Contents/Home
Default locale: en_US, platform encoding: MacRoman
OS name: "mac os x", version: "10.7.2", arch: "x86_64", family: "mac"</programlisting>
                <para>
                    If you receive an error indicating hat the "mvn" command could not be found, please ensure that the directory that includes the mvn 
                    executable (<emphasis role="bold">M2_HOME/bin</emphasis>) is on your machine's <emphasis role="bold">PATH</emphasis> environment variable.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Install and Setup Apache Tomcat</title>
            <para>KPME ${project.version} supports the following Tomcat versions:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Tomcat 6 (Servlet API 2.5, JSP 2.1) </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                Please visit the <link xlink:href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Apache Tomcat site</link> for information on how to install and configure Tomcat.
            </para>
            <para>Other servlet containers can be used with KPME, but this guide will focus on Tomcat.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Install KPME software from distribution</title>
            <para>
                The quickest way to get KPME installed is to download the binary distribution from the 
                <link xlink:href="http://kuali.org/kpme/download">kuali.org download site</link>. Once downloaded, decompress the software.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>    
    <section>
        <title>Building the KPME Database</title>
        <section>
            <title>Load KPME Database</title>
            <para>
                The KPME database release scripts contain all the SQL commands needed to install a new schema for version ${project.version} database using 
                Rice embedded mode with the database objects (tables, constraints, bootstrap data) for the KPME application.
            </para>
            <note>
                <para>
                    You will need to already have a working instance of a Rice ${rice.version} up and running since you will need to run sql statements against
                    that Rice database.
                </para>
            </note>
            <section>
	            <title>Prepare a KPME MySQL Database</title>
	            <orderedlist>
	                <listitem>
	                    <para>
	                        Create a MySQL user with a username of less than 8 characters.
	                    </para>
	                </listitem>
	                <listitem>
	                    <para>
	                        Create a MySQL default schema for the user with the default character set of UTF8.  If a different character set is desired, the 
	                        scripts will need to be updated to the new character set.
	                    </para>
	                </listitem>
	                <listitem>
	                    <para>
	                        Give the new MySQL user the following privileges on the schema:
	                        <itemizedlist>
	                            <listitem><para>SELECT</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>INSERT</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>UPDATE</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>DELETE</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>CREATE</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>DROP</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>INDEX</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>ALTER</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>CREATE_VIEW</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>CREATE_ROUTINE</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>ALTER_ROUTINE</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>CREATE_TMP_TABLE</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>LOCK_TABLES</para></listitem>
	                        </itemizedlist>
	                    </para>
	                </listitem>
	            </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Prepare a KPME Oracle Database</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Create an Oracle user with a username of less than 8 characters.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Give the new Oracle user the following privileges:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        DEFAULT TABLESPACE set to &lt;Users Tablespace&gt; (the intended location where the schema database structures and 
                                        base bootstrap data are stored).
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem><para>QUOTA UNLIMITED set to &lt;Users Tablespace&gt;</para></listitem>
                                <listitem><para>CREATE SESSION</para></listitem>
                                <listitem><para>CREATE SYNONYM</para></listitem>
                                <listitem><para>CREATE PROCEDURE</para></listitem>
                                <listitem><para>CREATE TRIGGER</para></listitem>
                                <listitem><para>CREATE TABLE</para></listitem>
                                <listitem><para>CREATE TYPE</para></listitem>
                                <listitem><para>CREATE VIEW</para></listitem>
                                <listitem><para>CREATE SEQUENCE</para></listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </para>
                        <note>
                            <para>
                                A user’s DEFAULT TABLESPACE is set with the CREATE USER statement or ALTER USER statement. The TABLESPACE should not be the 
                                SYSTEM tablespace.
                            </para>
                        </note>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Populate the KPME Database</title>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Change to the directory <emphasis role="bold">src/main/config/sql</emphasis>.  Go to the appropriate folder for the version of KPME 
                            you are installing and your database type.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Install the <emphasis role="bold">client.sql</emphasis> file on your KPME database and the 
                            <emphasis role="bold">server.sql</emphasis> file on your Rice database.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
	        <section>
	            <title>Verifying your Database Installation</title>
	            <para>
	               At this point, your KPME database should be successfully installed.  To verify this, log into your database and verify that tables exist.
                </para>
	        </section>
        </section>
    </section>    
    <section>
        <title>Configure KPME</title>
        <section>
            <title>Deploying the WAR file</title>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Copy the kpme-web.war file from the base directory of the distribution to the directory that contains web applications in your
                        servlet container. For Tomcat, this is <emphasis role="bold">&lt;Tomcat-root-directory&gt;/webapps</emphasis>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Copy the database-specific JDBC driver to the &lt;Tomcat-root-directory&gt;/lib.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
	                     Place <emphasis role="bold">src/main/config/local/kuali/*</emphasis> in the <emphasis role="bold">&lt;userhome&gt;/kuali</emphasis> 
	                     directory.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Configure the <emphasis role="bold">kpme-config.xml</emphasis> file and edit parameters as desired.</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
	                        <para>
	                             You will at least need to fill in the parameters listed in the <link linkend="configuration_parameters">Parameters</link> 
	                             section.
	                         </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
	                             Other commonly changed parameters are inherited from Rice and are normally changed to reflect the local settings for KPME: 
	                             <emphasis role="bold">application.url</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">app.context.name</emphasis>, 
	                             <emphasis role="bold">log4j.settings.path</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">log4j.settings.reloadInterval</emphasis>, 
	                             <emphasis role="bold">keystore.alias</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">keystore.file</emphasis>, 
	                             <emphasis role="bold">keystore.password</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="bold">encryption.key</emphasis>.  Please see the Rice
	                             documentation for more information.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>Startup Tomcat to deploy KPME.  Watch the logs to ensure that it started up successfully.</para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>
	                     The KPME application should now be accessible at <emphasis role="bold">http://localhost:8080/kpme-dev</emphasis>.
	                 </para>
	            </listitem>
	            <listitem>
	                <para>Login as 'admin.'  Ingest the KPME KEW documents.</para>
	                <itemizedlist>
	                    <listitem>
	                        <para>
	                            Click the System Admin tab and then select XML Ingester from the Workflow pane.
	                        </para>
	                    </listitem>
	                    <listitem>
	                        <para>
	                            Ingest all files in <emphasis role="bold">src/main/config/workflow/*</emphasis>.  Ingestion can take several minutes, 
	                            during which time the activity indicator on your browser will just stay animated.
	                        </para>
	                    </listitem>
	                </itemizedlist>
	            </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
	    <section xml:id="configuration_parameters"> 
	        <title>Parameters</title>
	        <para>
	            The tables below have the basic set of parameters for <emphasis role="bold">kpme-config.xml</emphasis> that you need to get an instance of KPME 
	            running.  Please use these tables as a beginning reference to modify your <emphasis role="bold">kpme-config.xml</emphasis> file.
	        </para>
	        <table frame="none">
                <title>Embedded Mode</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="3.0*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Parameter</entry>
                            <entry>Description</entry>
                            <entry>Examples or Values</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>rice.server.url</entry>
                            <entry>The external URL used to access the Rice instance.</entry>
                            <entry>http://localhost:9080/kr-dev</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>dev.mode</entry>
                            <entry>Whether or not the server is running in development mode.  Use false for production.</entry>
                            <entry>false</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>kim.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that KIM is running in.  Use EMBEDDED for embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>EMBEDDED</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>kcb.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that KCB is running in.  Use EMBEDDED for embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>EMBEDDED</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>kew.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that KEW is running in.  Use EMBEDDED for embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>EMBEDDED</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>ken.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that KIM is running in.  Use REMOTE for embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>REMOTE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>ksb.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that KSB is running in.  Use REMOTE for embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>REMOTE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>kns.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that KNS is running in.  Use LOCAL even in embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>LOCAL</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>krms.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that KRMS is running in.  Use REMOTE for embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>REMOTE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>coreservice.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that the core service is running in.  Use REMOTE for embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>REMOTE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>location.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that the location module is running in.  Use REMOTE for embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>REMOTE</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>core.mode</entry>
                            <entry>The mode that the core application is running in.  Use LOCAL even in embedded mode.</entry>
                            <entry>LOCAL</entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
	        <table frame="none">
	            <title>KPME Database</title>
	            <tgroup cols="3">
	                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.75*"/>
	                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.55*"/>
	                <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.34*"/>
	                <thead>
	                    <row>
	                        <entry>Parameter</entry>
	                        <entry>Description</entry>
	                        <entry>Examples or Values</entry>
	                    </row>
	                </thead>
	                <tbody>
	                    <row>
	                        <entry>datasource.ojb.platform</entry>
	                        <entry>OJB platform name</entry>
	                        <entry>Oracle9i or MySQL</entry>
	                    </row>
	                    <row>
	                        <entry>datasource.platform</entry>
	                        <entry>Rice platform class name</entry>
	                        <entry>
	                            <itemizedlist>
	                                <listitem>
	                                    <para>org.kuali.rice.core.database.platform.MySQLPlatform</para>
	                                </listitem>
	                                <listitem>
	                                    <para>org.kuali.rice.core.database.platform.OraclePlatform</para>
	                                </listitem>
	                            </itemizedlist>
	                        </entry>
	                    </row>
	                    <row>
	                        <entry>datasource.driver.name</entry>
	                        <entry>JDBC driver class name</entry>
	                        <entry>
	                            <itemizedlist>
	                                <listitem>
	                                    <para>com.mysql.jdbc.Driver</para>
	                                </listitem>
	                                <listitem>
	                                    <para>oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleDriver</para>
	                                </listitem>
	                            </itemizedlist>
	                        </entry>
	                    </row>
	                    <row>
	                        <entry>datasource.username</entry>
	                        <entry>Username for the database</entry>
	                        <entry/>
	                    </row>
	                    <row>
	                        <entry>datasource.password</entry>
	                        <entry>Password for the database</entry>
	                        <entry/>
	                    </row>
	                    <row>
	                        <entry>datasource.url </entry>
	                        <entry>JDBC URL to the database</entry>
	                        <entry>
	                            <itemizedlist>
	                                <listitem>
                                        <para>jdbc:mysql://localhost:3306/kpmedev</para>
                                    </listitem>
	                                <listitem>
	                                    <para>jdbc:oracle:thin:@localhost:1521:XE</para>
	                                </listitem>
	                            </itemizedlist>
	                        </entry>
	                    </row>
	                </tbody>
	            </tgroup>
	        </table>
	        <table frame="none">
                <title>Rice Database</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.75*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.55*"/>
                    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.34*"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Parameter</entry>
                            <entry>Description</entry>
                            <entry>Examples or Values</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>server.datasource.ojb.platform</entry>
                            <entry>OJB platform name</entry>
                            <entry>Oracle9i or MySQL</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>server.datasource.platform</entry>
                            <entry>Rice platform class name</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>org.kuali.rice.core.database.platform.MySQLPlatform</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>org.kuali.rice.core.database.platform.OraclePlatform</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>server.datasource.driver.name</entry>
                            <entry>JDBC driver class name</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>com.mysql.jdbc.Driver</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleDriver</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>server.datasource.username</entry>
                            <entry>Username for the database</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>server.datasource.password</entry>
                            <entry>Password for the database</entry>
                            <entry/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>server.datasource.url </entry>
                            <entry>JDBC URL to the database</entry>
                            <entry>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>jdbc:mysql://localhost:3306/krdev</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>jdbc:oracle:thin:@localhost:1521:XE</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
	    </section>
	</section>
</chapter>